<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of Amicia daughter of Hvgh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein it is proved that Sir Peter Leicester Baronet, in his book entituled, Historical antiquities in two books, the first treating in general of Great Britain and Ireland, the second containing particular remarks concerning Cheshire, hath without any just ground declared the said Amicia to be a bastard/ by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
            <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13587058</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13587058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100577</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 465:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of Amicia daughter of Hvgh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein it is proved that Sir Peter Leicester Baronet, in his book entituled, Historical antiquities in two books, the first treating in general of Great Britain and Ireland, the second containing particular remarks concerning Cheshire, hath without any just ground declared the said Amicia to be a bastard/ by Sir Thomas Mainwaring ...</title>
                  <author>Mainwaring, Thomas, Sir, 1623-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Lowndes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
               <term>Leycester, Peter, --  Sir, 1614-1678. --  Historical antiquities.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:1"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF AMICIA, Daughter of <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH CYVELIOK,</hi> Earl of CHESTER.</p>
            <p>Wherein it is proved, That Sir <hi>Peter Leicester</hi> Baronet, In his Book, Entituled, <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities,</hi> In Two Books;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The firſt Treating in General of Great</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The ſecond containing Particular Remarks concerning</hi> Cheſhire</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Hath without any juſt Ground declared the ſaid <hi>Amicia</hi> to be a Baſtard.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Lowades</hi> over againſt <hi>Exeter</hi> Houſe in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>Peter Leicester,</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will appear very ſtrange to thoſe who know the nearneſs of Blood that is betwixt us, that I ſhould appear in Print againſt you; and I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, it is not without ſome regret, that I am conſtrained ſo to do: If you would have been contented to have delivered what you did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, concerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> Earl of
<pb facs="tcp:100577:3"/>
               <hi>Chester,</hi> as an uncertainty onely (as you have done that of <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>) you know I would have reſted ſatisfied with the Judgment of thoſe many know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unconcerned Perſons that have diſſented from you therein, and would never have given you and the Reader the trouble of any one of theſe Lines. But ſince you were ſo fond of divulging this your ſuppoſed new Diſcovery (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your being deſcended of her) as to determine her in your late publiſhed Book, abſolutely to be a Baſtard; and did alſo many years ſince, without any other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion at all, ſend a Paper tending to the ſame purpoſe, to a then De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty Herald (though at that time you did wholly miſtake the ſtate of the Caſe) I hope it will not be
<pb facs="tcp:100577:3"/>taken ill if I endeavor to give her a publick Vindication.</p>
            <p>I might here take occaſion to tell you, that I very much wonder, when you mention <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> Cheif Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and his Son <hi>Roger,</hi> and <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> Younger Son of the ſaid <hi>Roger,</hi> (which <hi>William</hi> had <hi>Over</hi> or <hi>Higher Peover</hi> by gift of his ſaid Father) that you do not take notice that they were all three Knights, you having ſeen proof thereof by many Deeds, where the word <hi>Dominus</hi> is prefixed to each of their names, which was not (that I know of) uſed to be done to any in thoſe elder Ages, but thoſe that were Knights (Clergy Men onely excepted) and accordingly in the 330 and 332 Pages of your Book, you own Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:100577:4"/>
               <hi>Warmincham,</hi> to be a Knight upon the like Proofs; as alſo, why you have not in the deſcent of the <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> of <hi>Peover,</hi> ſet down <hi>Ranul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus</hi> that is mentioned in <hi>Domeſday</hi> Book (whom you truly ſuppoſe to be a <hi>Mainwaring</hi>) as alſo all the other <hi>Mainwarings</hi> that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the aforeſaid Sir <hi>William Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> in regard they held <hi>Over-Peover,</hi> or the moſt part thereof, as well as they held <hi>Warmincham.</hi> For, that <hi>Tadetune</hi> which <hi>Ranulfus</hi> in <hi>Domeſday</hi> Book is ſaid to hold in <hi>Mildestric</hi> Hundred is <hi>Warmincham,</hi> it appearing by Ancient Records, that <hi>Manerium de Tetton &amp; Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium de Warmincham est unum &amp; idem Manerium;</hi> and it is alſo clear, that <hi>Ranulfus</hi> was a <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> becauſe, though he be there named without a Sirname, as <hi>Odard</hi> or <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100577:4"/>(the owner of a part of <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) and many others were, yet the Sirname of <hi>Meſnilwaren</hi> or <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> (for that name in Records and Deeds is written very many ways) was as appears in your Book Pag. 111. uſed in the days of King <hi>William Rufus</hi> (as it alſo was ever ſince) and all the Lands that the ſaid <hi>Ranulfus</hi> had in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> which are mentioned in your Book, Pag. 422, 423, 426, 427. As alſo all the Lands that <hi>Ranulfus</hi> held in <hi>Norfolk</hi> were enjoyed by the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Mainwarings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might alſo here take notice of your miſtake in the 336 Page of your Book, where you blame the Herald for making, in Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> time, for the then Sir <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Mainwarings</hi> Coat <hi>Barry of Twelve pieces Argent and Gules</hi> (for
<pb facs="tcp:100577:5"/>which you cite <hi>Guillims</hi> Heraldry) but that was the miſtake of <hi>Guillim,</hi> and not of the Herald, as appears by the Pedegree then made, which you have often ſeen. For, the Coat which the Herald did then allow the ſaid Sir <hi>Randle</hi> to have a Right unto (as well as to thoſe two placed in your Book, P. 331. and 333. the firſt whereof, though cut right, is by you blazoned amiſs) was <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſix Barulets Gules,</hi> which Coat you take notice Sir <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> did Seal with; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Line of the ſaid Sir <hi>Roger Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> preſently failing (Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwaring</hi> Eldeſt Son of the ſaid Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> having iſſue Sir <hi>Warine Mainwaring,</hi> who had iſſue a Daughter and Heir) I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but the <hi>Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>Peover,</hi> who (as is confeſſed by you Pag.
<pb facs="tcp:100577:5"/>333.) are now next Heir-Male to the <hi>Mainwarings</hi> of <hi>Warmincham,</hi> have a good right to the <hi>Six Barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> with which Sir <hi>Roger Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of <hi>Warmincham,</hi> Father of Sir <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> did Seal, as well as they have to the <hi>Two Bars,</hi> which Sir <hi>Thomas Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> of <hi>Warmincham,</hi> Brother of the ſaid Sir <hi>William Mainwaring</hi> did bear.</p>
            <p>I might in like manner here, let you know that I do ſuſpect you have branded ſeveral Perſons in your Book with <hi>Baſtardy,</hi> without direct Proof thereof. And although I ſhall not concern my ſelf for any, but ſome of thoſe which are by you mentioned, when you write of the baſe Iſſue of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok;</hi> yet if I make it appear that you have there without any certainty
<pb facs="tcp:100577:6"/>aſperſed two other Ladies beſides <hi>Amicia.</hi> I hope you will have no juſt cauſe to blame,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate KINSMAN and Servant <hi>Thomas Mainwaring.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Baddeley,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 27. 1672/3.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100577:6"/>
            <head>The Words of Sir <hi>Peter Leiceſter,</hi> concerning <hi>Amicia,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester,</hi> in his <hi>Historical Antiquities.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Pag.</hi> 134, 135, 136, 137, and 138.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>IV. <hi>The Baſe Iſſue of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aganus, Dominus de Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>whom I have ſeen wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to a Deed, ſubſcribed thus</hi>—</p>
               <p>Filius Baſtardus Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Comitis Ceſtriae.</p>
               <p>Roger, <hi>witneſs to a Deed of his Brother</hi> Randles, <hi>to the Abbey of S.</hi> Werburge, <hi>whom I conceive was a Baſtard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100577:7"/>Amicia, <hi>the Wife of</hi> Ralph Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>ſometime Judge of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>to whom</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>her Father, gave</hi> In libero maritagio ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Gilib. filii Rogeri, ſcilicet ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium trium Militum: Faciendo ſibi ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium duorum Militum, <hi>as the words of the Original Deed do run now in the Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sir</hi> Thomas Mainwaring <hi>of</hi> Over Peover <hi>Baronet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo, another Baſe Daughter, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, Married one</hi> Bacun, <hi>and had Iſſue</hi> Richard Bacun, <hi>Founder of the Priory of</hi> Rouceſter <hi>in</hi> Staffordſhire, <hi>about the Reign of King</hi> John; <hi>for the ſafety of his Soul, and the Soul of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> Randle, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter. Monaſt. Part 2. pag. 267.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And here I cannot but miſlike the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance of that Herald, who gave to</hi> Mainwaring <hi>of</hi> Peover, <hi>the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter<hi>'s Coat of Arms. Which device was never done before the Raign of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>in the time of Sir</hi> Randle Mainwaring, <hi>late of</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>the Elder, my Grandfather by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for if he ought of right to Quarter that Coat, then muſt he be deſcended from a Coheir to the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>but that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100577:7"/>he was not; for, the Coheirs of Earl</hi> Hugh, <hi>as you ſee before, were married to Four of the greateſt Peers of the Kingdom, the Earl of</hi> Huntington, <hi>the Earl of</hi> Arundel, <hi>the Earl of</hi> Derby, <hi>and the Earl of</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter<hi>'s Son and Heir, who lived not to be Earl: Neither was</hi> Mainwaring <hi>then an equal Competitor to have Married a Coheir to the Earl of</hi> Cheſter; <hi>and it is plain,</hi> Ex Placitis, 18 Hen. 3. Rot. 14. <hi>in the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>where the Coheirs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plead</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Scot, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>for their part; there is no mention of</hi> Amice <hi>claiming any part, or any from or under her in the Record: Beſides, all Antient Authors of thoſe times, as</hi> Polychronicon, Matthew Paris, Knighton, Stow, <hi>and others, would not have omitted her amongſt the reſt which they have ſet down, had ſhe been a Coheir, which alſo ſhe muſt needs have been, had ſhe been Legitimate; for</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>never had any other Wife but</hi> Bertred, <hi>and ſhe ſurvived him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And though</hi> Amice, <hi>in the Deed before mentioned, is ſtiled</hi> Filia Hugonis Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitis, <hi>without the Addition or Note of Baſtard; it was very uſual in thoſe elder ages ſo to do: The like we find of</hi> Geva, <hi>Baſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100577:8"/>Daughter of</hi> Hugh Lupus, <hi>and ſeveral others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>V. <hi>Concerning this</hi> Bertred, <hi>the Wife of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>I cannot omit the Falſities and Abſurdities of ſome Authors, as</hi> Powel <hi>on the</hi> Welſh Hiſtory, p. 295. <hi>and</hi> Ferne <hi>in his</hi> Lacy's Nobility, p. 53. <hi>Both of them calling this</hi> Bertred <hi>by the name of</hi> Beatrix, <hi>and ſaying ſhe was the Daughter of</hi> Richard Lucy, <hi>Cheif Juſtice of</hi> England, <hi>a moſt groſs falſity. I am very certain, that</hi> Hugh Cyvelioks <hi>Wife was not Daughter of</hi> Lucy, <hi>nor ever called</hi> Beatrix <hi>in any old Deed or Record, though I find by good authority that there was a Woman called</hi> Beatrix Lucy, <hi>but never Wife of Earl</hi> Hugh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Death of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok. Obiit.</hi> 1181.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis</hi> Hugh, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>died at</hi> Leek <hi>in</hi> Staffordſhire, <hi>and was buried at</hi> Cheſter, Anno Dom. 1181. 27 Hen. 2. Hoveden, Pag. 615. <hi>With whom,</hi> Weſtminſter, Polychronicon, <hi>and</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100577:8"/>Cambden inter Comites Ceſtriae, <hi>do all agree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He was Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>Twenty eight years, and gave the Church of</hi> Bettesford <hi>to the Prior and Canons of</hi> Trentham, <hi>after the death of</hi> William Barba, <hi>who at the time of this Grant poſſeſſed the ſame, a Copy of which Deed, I received from Sir</hi> Simon Dews <hi>Baronet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now becauſe I find that ſome are diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at my placing of</hi> Amice, <hi>ſometime the Wife of</hi> Ralph Mainwaring, <hi>Judge of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>among the Baſe Iſſue of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter; <hi>and alſo, that I am informed that three eminent Judges and four Heralds, are of opinion, That ſhe was Legitimate, and not a Baſe Daughter of Earl</hi> Hugh. <hi>It is very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that I put down here my Reaſons why I have ſo placed her, protesting withal, that I have not done it out of any prejudicate opinion, or calumny intended in the leaſt, but onely for the truths ſake according to the beſt of my judgment, and that after a long and diligent ſcrutiny made herein; for I muſt ever acknowledge my ſelf to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of the Loyns of this</hi> Amice, <hi>by my own Mother; but you know the old ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of</hi> Ariſtotle, Amicus Plato, Amicus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100577:9"/>Socrates, Sed magis amica veritas. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were Baſtards in thoſe elder Ages of ſuch diſrepute as now in our days,</hi> Memini me alicubi legiſſe (<hi>ſaith</hi> Spelman <hi>in his</hi> Gloſſary <hi>on the word</hi> Baſtardus) Priſcos ſeptentrionales Populos etiam ſpurios admiſiſſe in ſucceſſionem; <hi>and where he farther tells us, that King</hi> William <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror began his Letter to</hi> Alan, <hi>Earl of</hi> Little Britain, <hi>as he did many other more, in theſe words,</hi> Ego Willielmus cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento Baſtardus. <hi>Of which Title (it ſeems) he was not aſhamed, otherwiſe he would never have uſed it himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And therefore the Queſtion being no more then this, Whether</hi> Amice <hi>was a Baſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or no? I will firſt anſwer thoſe Reaſons which ſeem to be the chief ground of thoſe worthy Perſons aboveſaid, who think</hi> Amice <hi>was no Baſtard, and then in order ſet down my own Reaſons, why I conceive her to be a Baſtard; ſubmitting my ſelf wholly to the judgment of all Learned Perſons herein.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100577:9"/>
               <head>The Reaſons that She was no Baſtard.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, <hi>Our Common Law alloweth not that any Lands can paſs</hi> in libero Maritagio <hi>with a Baſtard Daughter,</hi> Coke upon Littl. fol. 21. b. <hi>And therefore</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mice <hi>having Land given with her</hi> in libero Maritagio <hi>by the Deed, it muſt be preſumed that ſhe was no Baſtard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>To which I anſwer, That it is true, the Law is ſo taken at this day with us; but that the Law was ſo taken in the elder ages of</hi> Henry <hi>the Second, when</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>lived and upwards, I very much doubt; and if we mark well this Grant, it is the Grant of Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>to</hi> Ralph Mainwaring <hi>with</hi> Amice <hi>his Daughter, in Frank-marriage of the Service of</hi> Gilbert, <hi>Son of</hi> Roger, <hi>to wit, the Service of three Knights Fees, by doing the Service of two Knights Fees to the ſaid Earl and his Heirs; which is rather a Releaſe of the Service of one Knights Fee, then the Grant of any Land. But to paſs by this — I ſay, That the Common Law in ſundry things is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100577:10"/>altered at this day, from what it was in former Ages, long after</hi> Henry <hi>the Second,</hi> Coke upon Littl. fol. 34. Sect. 39. Coke ibid. fol. 3. a. fol. 8. a. <hi>At the bottome of the Page, and on the other ſide</hi> (b) <hi>at the bottome,</hi> Fol. 26. b. Sect. 29. <hi>and infinite other particulars may be cited. And that in this particular alſo of paſſing Land</hi> in libero Maritagio <hi>with Baſtards, the Law ſeems clearly to be altered herein ſince the Reign of</hi> Henry <hi>the Second. For, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practiſe I take to be the Common Law, and I ſhall give you here one Precedent made about the Raign of King</hi> Stephen <hi>(and doubtleſs many others might be muſtered up from thoſe elder ages, if any curious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would take pains to ſearch old Deeds and Records) which Deed I received from Sir</hi> Simon Dewes, <hi>tranſcribed out of a Manuſcript in</hi> Arundel <hi>Houſe in</hi> London, <hi>belonging antiently to the Barons of</hi> Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>wherein the old Charts belonging to the</hi> Baſſets <hi>of</hi> Drayton-Baſſets <hi>in</hi> Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire <hi>where inrolled about</hi> Richards <hi>the Second's time.</hi> Ibid. fol. 67. a.</p>
               <p>Ranulfus Comes Ceſtriae Willielmo Conſtabulario &amp; Roberto Dapifero &amp; omnibus Baronibus ſuis &amp; hominibus Francis &amp; Anglicis totius Angliae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100577:10"/>Sciatis me dediſſe &amp; conceſſiſſe Gevae Ridell Filiae Comitis Hughes Draytunam cum pertinentiis in libero conjugio, ſicuti Comes Hughes ei in libero conjugio dedit &amp; conceſſit. Et teneat bene &amp; in pace, honorifice, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere ut melius &amp; liberiûs tenuit tempore Hugonis Comitis &amp; aliorum meorum an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teceſſorum eiſdem conſuetudinibus &amp; libertatibus. Teſtibus Gilberto Filio Ricardi, &amp; Adelizâ forore meâ, &amp; Willielmo Blundo, &amp; Alexandro de Treſgor, &amp; Rogero de Bellocampo, &amp; Willielmo de Sais, &amp; Roberto de Sais, &amp; Ricardo Filio Aluredi, &amp; Hugone Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Osberti, &amp; Henrico de Chalder: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Saintonam.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein</hi> Geva <hi>is called Daughter of Earl</hi> Hugh Lupus, <hi>as</hi> Amice <hi>in that other Deed is termed Daughter of Earl</hi> Hugh Cyveliok. <hi>Now that</hi> Geva <hi>was a Baſtard is very plain out of</hi> Ordericus, <hi>a Man that lived in that very age, he tells us,</hi> Lib. 10. pag. 787. <hi>ſpeaking of</hi> Hugh Lupus <hi>his death</hi> — Richardus pulcherrimus puer quem ſolum ex Ermentrude Filia Hugonis de Claromonte genuit, &amp;c. Richard, <hi>a brave youth; whom onely</hi> Hugh Lupus <hi>begot on</hi> Ermentrude, <hi>Daughter of</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100577:11"/>Hugh de Claremonte, &amp;c. <hi>Nor can this be reſtrained to the onely Son, for then it must have been otherways expreſſed; and if</hi> Hugh Lupus <hi>had any other Son or Daughter by</hi> Ermentrude, <hi>then cannot</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard <hi>be ſaid onely to be begotten on her by Earl</hi> Hugh, <hi>and ſo</hi> Geva <hi>was a Baſtard, or elſe</hi> Ordericus <hi>lies. Alſo the ſame Author tells us,</hi> Lib. 4. p. 522. <hi>that</hi> Hugh Lupus <hi>had alſo many Baſe Sons and Daughters by ſeveral Strumpets, who were almoſt all ſwept away by ſundry misfortunes; and very probably, if</hi> Hugh Lupus <hi>had any more Legitimate Children by his Wife, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Earl</hi> Richard, <hi>either Son or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Ordericus <hi>would have Recorded them as well as he hath put down others in like Nature, being indeed his uſual method through the whole courſe of his Hiſtory. And had</hi> Geva <hi>been Legitimate, then her Iſſue ought rather to have ſucceeded into the Earldom of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>then</hi> Randle de Meſchines, <hi>after the Death of</hi> Richard, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>for as much as the Siſter and her Heirs, ought to inherit before the Aunt and her Heirs; and howbeit many Earldoms have deſcended to the Heirs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males, and not to the Heirs General, yet in this caſe were no Heirs-male, but two
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100577:11"/>Females, an Aunt Legitimate, who had it, and a Siſter not Legitimate: And ſhow me a Precedent, where ever the Heirs of an Aunt inherited before the Heirs of a Siſter, both legally born, and no Heirs-male left, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in caſe of Forfeiture by Treaſon, or ſome other great cauſe to hinder the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Add to theſe the words of</hi> Glanvile, <hi>Cheif Juſtice of</hi> England, <hi>who lived under</hi> Henry <hi>the Second, in that very age with</hi> Amice, Lib. 7. cap. 1. Quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet liber homo quandam partem terrae ſuae cum Filia ſua, vel cum aliqua alia qualibet muliere dare poteſt in Marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium. ſive habuerit haeredem, ſive non, velit haeres vel non, imò &amp; eo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicente. <hi>And if a Man might give Land then in Free-marriage with any Woman whatſoever, then he might give it to his Baſtard, and then the Law is now changed, for now it muſt be of the Donors Blood, and a Baſtard is now ſaid not to be of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors Blood,</hi> Quaſi nullius Filius, <hi>and it ſeems to me, that in thoſe elder ages, Baſtards were reputed of the Blood by the frequent appellation of them by the names of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, Brother, Daughter, Son, and Coſin: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, our Laws were then imperfect, dark, and obſcure in moſt things, till</hi> Bracton,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100577:12"/>
                  <hi>under King</hi> Henry <hi>the Third, compiled the Body of our Laws, and brought them into a method.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now I have done concerning this cheif Reaſon, whereupon thoſe worthy Judges grounded their Opinions; and we daily ſee Opinions of Lawyers follow the putting of the Caſe, which many times up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mature deliberation, and hearing of the Caſe well argued, may then be of another Opinion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now follow the Arguments of leſſer moment, which I perſwade my ſelf were no Grounds for the Judges aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>THe diſparity of the years between</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>and</hi> Bertred <hi>his Wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may ſuppoſe he had a former Wife; for</hi> Bertred <hi>was but Twenty ſix years old at the Death of Earl</hi> Hugh 1181. <hi>as appears by the Inquiſition taken</hi> 30 H. 2. 1183. <hi>after the death of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok; <hi>and</hi> Hugh <hi>was Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>Twenty eight years, which was one or two years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Bertred <hi>was born; beſides what years were run up of his age before his Father</hi> Randle <hi>died, which may be ſuppoſed to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100577:12"/>a competent term of years; and then it is probably he had a former Wife, and that he ſtaid not unmarried ſo long as till</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>was fit for marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Now let us examine the Matter a little, it will give us ſome light,</hi> Robert, <hi>Earl of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>married</hi> Mabill, <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Heir of</hi> Robert Fitz-Haimon, Anno Dom. 1110. <hi>So</hi> Stow <hi>in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle. See alſo</hi> Seldon<hi>'s</hi> Tit. Hon. pag. 647. <hi>By her he had Iſſue four Sons and two Daughters.</hi> Maud, <hi>the younger Daughter married</hi> Randle de Gernoniis, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>Father to</hi> Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok. Vincent upon Brook, p. 216. <hi>Now ſuppoſe we,</hi> Maud <hi>to be the fourth Child, probably ſhe was not born till about the year</hi> 1117. <hi>or thereabout; and that about the year</hi> 1139. <hi>ſhe was married to Earl</hi> Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, <hi>whereby</hi> Robert, <hi>Earl of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>ſtrengthned his party for</hi> Maud <hi>the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; at that time ſhe cannot well be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be above Twenty two years old, if ſhe were ſo much. Now Earl</hi> Randle <hi>died</hi> 1153. <hi>So that</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>could not poſſibly be above Twelve years old at his Fathers death, he might be much leſs: But ſuppoſe we in a middle way, that he was ſix years old at his Fathers death, which is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100577:13"/>more then can be well affirmed, then could not Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>be above Seven or eight years elder then</hi> Bertred <hi>his Wife; And what great matter is this? I my ſelf was eight years older then my Wife when I was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried; but it is much more probable that he never had any other Wife, becauſe he had many Baſtard Sons and Daughters, whoſe heat of youth might by a very timely mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, have been poſſibly prevented, or at leaſt aſſwaged in ſome meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. Bertred, <hi>the Wife of</hi> Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok, <hi>was a witneſs to the Deed in Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage with</hi> Amice, <hi>and</hi> Amice <hi>had a Daughter called</hi> Bertred, <hi>after the name of the Counteſs.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Probably</hi> Amice <hi>was no Bastard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Truly this is of ſo little weight that it will need no anſwer; for I yet appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend no reaſon in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Roger Mainwaring, <hi>Son of</hi> Ralph Mainwaring, <hi>calls</hi> Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devil, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>and</hi> Lincoln, <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle in another Deed; wherefore it is to be ſuppoſed that</hi> Amice <hi>was no Bastard, otherwiſe</hi> Roger <hi>durſt not have preſumed to have called the Earl <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100577:13"/>Anſw. <hi>Hiſtories, Deeds, and Records, are full of Examples in this nature, where we find Baſtards frequently called Coſin, Brother, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, Son, and Danghter. For example,</hi> Robert, <hi>Earl of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>Baſe Son of King</hi> Henry <hi>the Firſt, is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called in Histories, Brother to</hi> Maud <hi>the Empreſs,</hi> Hoveden. p. 553. <hi>He is alſo ſo ſtiled in a Deed made by</hi> Maud <hi>the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs her ſelf,</hi> Seldon<hi>'s</hi> Tit. Hon. p. 649. <hi>Called alſo Coſin to King</hi> Stephen, Orderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, pag. 922. Reginald, <hi>Earl of</hi> Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wal, <hi>another Baſe Son of</hi> Henry <hi>the Firſt, ſtiled</hi> Avunculus Regis Henrici Secundi, <hi>by</hi> Hoveden, pag. 536. Robert <hi>and</hi> Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiwel, <hi>two Baſtard Sons of</hi> Hugh Lupus, <hi>frequently called</hi> Filii Hugonis Comitis Ceſtriae, <hi>and</hi> Ottiwel <hi>ſtiled</hi> Frater Ricar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Comitis Ceſtriae, Ordericus, p. 602. &amp; 783. &amp; 870. Geva <hi>a Baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Lupus, <hi>ſtiled in old Deeds</hi> Filia Hugonis Comitis; <hi>and there alſo ſhe calls Earl</hi> Randle <hi>her Coſin,</hi> Monaſticon, Part 1. pag. 439. <hi>Alſo</hi> Richard Bacon, <hi>Son of another Baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liok, <hi>calls</hi> Randle Blundevil, <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, in another Deed, as</hi> Mainwaring <hi>in like manner here ſtiles him in this Deed,</hi> Monaſticon. Part 2.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100577:14"/>p. 267. <hi>Every Man that is but the leaſt verſed in Antiquities, knows theſe things to be very uſual.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Reaſons that <hi>Amice</hi> was a Baſtard.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>IF</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>had no other Wife but</hi> Bertred, <hi>then</hi> Amice <hi>muſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be a Baſtard; for ſhe was not a Daughter by</hi> Bertred, <hi>as is granted on all ſides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>never had any other Wife but</hi> Bertred. Ergo, Amice <hi>was a Baſtard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Minor is to be proved by the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmer,</hi> Oportet Affirmantem probare: <hi>For as yet I never ſaw the leaſt proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either by Deed, Record, or any Ancient Hiſtorian, nor yet any inducement of good reaſon to incline my belief of it; and till this be done, it is unreaſonable to impoſe it upon any Mans belief, by ſuppoſing that he had another Wife, for ſuppoſitions are no proof at all. It is not enough to ſuppoſe</hi> Amice <hi>might be by a former Wife, but it muſt be clearly proved, or ſtrongly inferred
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100577:14"/>from ſolid Reaſon, that it is ſo, and that</hi> Hugh <hi>had a former Wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither is it a ſufficient anſwer hereunto to ſay, That it is unreaſonable to conclude all Children Baſtards, whoſe Mothers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved, God forbid: But in this Caſe we find a Wife certainly Recorded, and a Son and four Daughters (who were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Coheirs, and carried away all Earl</hi> Hugh<hi>'s Lands) clearly proved by Records, and Antient Hiſtorians; and alſo Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>is certainly known to have had many Baſtards both Sons and Daughters, which gives occaſion of ſtrong ſuſpition, that</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mice <hi>was a Baſtard, ſhe being neither Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by any Hiſtorian, nor ever had or claimed any Land as a Coheir; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here is a neceſſity of proving a former Wife; which, for my part, I believe firmly Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>never had.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Whatſoever is given in Frank-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, is given as a Portion. Now the Releaſe of the Service of one Knights Fee in Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage, ſeems not a competent Portion for a Legitimate Daughter of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>eſpecially for the eldeſt Daughter, for ſo ſhe muſt be, being of the firſt venter, which always is more worthy then the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100577:15"/>if ſhe were at all Legitimate. And we find the other Daughters married to four of the greateſt Earls in</hi> England. <hi>All which is a ſtrong preſumption, that</hi> Amice <hi>was a Baſtard and no Legitimate Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To this it may be anſwered, That poſſibly Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>might give</hi> Amice <hi>a great Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Money, though ſhe had no Lands; and I ſay poſſibly too, he might give her no Money, or at leaſt nothing conſiderable. Which great Portion in Money, when it ſhall appear to be true, may take off the ſtrength of this Argument or Second Reaſon, till then it muſt be very preſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Antient Hiſtorians of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as</hi> Polychronicon, <hi>writ by the Monk of</hi> Cheſter, Henry Knighton, <hi>the Monk of</hi> Leiceſter, <hi>and others; alſo</hi> Stow <hi>and</hi> Cambden <hi>have Recorded the lawful Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Coheirs of Earl</hi> Hugh. <hi>And ſo the Record of</hi> 18 Hen. 3. <hi>And had</hi> Amice <hi>been a Legitimate Daughter, it is likely that theſe Historians would not all have omitted her, but of her there is</hi> Altum ſilentium <hi>among all the Hiſtorians and Records which I have yet ſeen, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100577:15"/>I look upon this onely as a probable, not as a ſure evincing Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe were the Reaſons which inclined my Opinion to place</hi> Amice <hi>in that order as I have done; but ſince there are ſome Learned Men of another Opinion, I muſt leave every Perſon to the dictate of his own Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:16"/>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100577:16"/>
            <head>THE DEFENCE OF <hi>AMICIA,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do very much wonder that you ſhould ſo peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily call <hi>Amicia</hi> a Baſe Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyneliok,</hi> unleſs you had more ſure grounds to go upon: And though it be onely my task to defend the ſaid <hi>Amicia,</hi> yet I do ſuppoſe I ſhall make it appear before I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100577:17"/>have done, that you go upon no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute certainty, in calling her that was Mother to <hi>Richard Bacun,</hi> Founder of the Priory of <hi>Roucester</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Baſe Daughter of the ſaid <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> or in calling <hi>Geva</hi> a Baſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Lupus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At preſent give me leave to remind you what you have been formerly told, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe Heralds that gave to <hi>Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Peover</hi> the quartering of the Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi>'s Coat in Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s time, were Mr. <hi>William Cambden</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sampſon Erdeſwick</hi> (Perſons, who very well underſtood themſelves) and I do not know why you ſhould ſo much miſlike their boldneſs and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (as you call it) for their ſo doing: For, though we did not antiently quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Coat, it not being uſual in that age, when that match was made, for any ſo to do; and that it may perhaps in ſtrictneſs be true, that it doth yet onely belong to thoſe of the whole Blood to Quarter Coats, and that to ſhew their Right; yet it being now a common practiſe for thoſe who are of the half Blood alſo to do it, to manifeſt, That they deſcend of the ſame Father that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100577:17"/>thoſe of the whole Blood do, I know not why it ſhould be accounted a crime in us, more then in others in the like Caſe.</p>
            <p>As for your Objecting, That <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> was not then an equal Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to have married a Coheir of the Ear! of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> the Coheirs being mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Four of the greateſt Peers of the Kingdom: We do not ſay, That he either was an equal Competitor, or that ſhe was a Coheir to Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> ſhe being the Daughter to <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> by a former Wife, and ſo but half Siſter to the ſaid Earl <hi>Randle;</hi> however, that could have been no ſubſtantial Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove that <hi>Amicia</hi> was not Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe, ſometimes ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons have the fortune to marry Wives far beyond their Degrees or Eſtates.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither was Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> ſo inconſiderable a Perſon, as perhaps you may conceit him to be. For, beſides that, Sir <hi>Roger Mainwaring,</hi> Son of the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph,</hi> did after the death of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100577:18"/>ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> give to Sir <hi>William Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> his younger Son, <hi>Peover,</hi> as alſo ſome other Lands; the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> had alſo the Lordſhip of <hi>Waburne</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and the Lordſhips (or great part) of <hi>Rode, Blakenhal, Warmincham, Northerden, Aſhton juxta Kelſall, Henbury,</hi> and <hi>Pexhull. Willaſton, Great Warford, Little Warford, Whelock, Winnington, Cokiſhall, Tatton, Senelleſtune, Smalwood,</hi> and half of <hi>Pichmere,</hi> as alſo other Lands in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> the moſt of which came to Sir <hi>William Truſſel,</hi> who about <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt's time, married <hi>Matilda,</hi> the ſole Daughter and Heir of Sir <hi>Warine Mainwaring,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>Thomas Mainwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>Roger,</hi> Son of the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> and <hi>Amicia:</hi> And the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> was Cheif Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> which antiently hath been a place of that great repute that Dukes of <hi>York, Gloceſter, Exeter,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and Earls of <hi>Nottingham, Wiltſhire, Suffolk, Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and <hi>Derby;</hi> beſides, other great Perſons have heretofore enjoyed the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither was the Caſe the ſame with the other Daughters of the Earl of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100577:18"/>
               <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> married with <hi>Amicia,</hi> as it was afterward, for <hi>Amicia</hi> was married in the life time of her Father Earl <hi>Hugh;</hi> whereas thoſe Four came to be ſuch great Fortunes upon the death of their Brother <hi>Randle,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln,</hi> without Iſſue, to whom they then became Heirs, they being his Siſters of the whole Blood; and though all, or moſt of them were married before they came to be his Heirs, yet the ſaid Earl <hi>Randle</hi> having never had Iſſue, the expectation of that Eſtate added to their other Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, muſt needs make them very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Fortunes; whereas <hi>Amicia</hi> was but of the half Blood, being a Daughter of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> by a former Wife.</p>
            <p>And whereas you do acknowledge that you have been informed, That Three eminent Judges, and Four He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds are of opinion that <hi>Amicia</hi> was Legitimate, and not a Baſe Daughter, you received that information ſeveral years ago; but you were alſo lately told by one, whom I hope, you have no reaſon to diſcredit; that ſince then, ſeveral other Learned Judges and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100577:19"/>had been conſulted. All which did concur in the ſame opinion, that <hi>Amicia</hi> was Legitimate.</p>
            <p>But before I come to the Reaſons that are by you alleaged, either for or againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> give me leave to recite theſe Three Deeds following, that thoſe who read them, and the Reaſons on both ſides, may clearly underſtand the full State of the Caſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go Comes Ceſtr' Conſtabular' Dapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer' &amp; omnibus Baronibus ſuis &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis Ballivis &amp; hominibus ſuis Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis &amp; Anglicis tam praeſentibus quam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis ſalutem. Sciatis me dediſſe &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiſſe &amp; hac praeſenti Karta mea confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe Radulpho de Menilwarin cum Amicia Filia mea in libero maritagio ſervitium Gilib. filii Rogeri, ſcilicet, ſervitium tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Militum faciendo michi ſervitium duorum Militum ille &amp; haeredes ſui michi &amp; haeredibus meis, quare volo &amp; firmiter praecipio ut nullus ſuper hoc eum vel haeredes ſuos vexet, vel amplius quam ſervitium duorum Militum de hoc praedicto tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to requirat. Teſte R. Abbate Ceſtr. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treia Comitiſſa Ceſtr. Sim. Thuſchet, Rogero de Livet, Gilib. filio Pigot. Rob. fratre
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100577:19"/>ſuo, Frumb. de Ridford. Willielmo de Mei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilwarin, Rob. filio Ham. Bettr. Cam. Rob. de Meinilwarin, Ran. de Lee, Rad. Clerico, Petro Clerico qui hanc Kartam fecit &amp; multis aliis apud Lee.</p>
               <p>RAdulfus de Meidnilwar' omnibus praeſentibus &amp; futuris ad quos praeſens ſcriptum pervenerit ſalutem. Saiatis me dediſſe &amp; conceſſiſſe &amp; praeſenti carta mea confirmaſſe Henrico de Alditelegh in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berum maritagium cum Bertrea filia mea Smelewde cum pertinentiis &amp; Senelleſt': Cum pertinent. &amp; dimid' Pichemere cum pertinentiis ſuis &amp; i. Marc. de reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu annuo in Civitate Ceſtr' de terra quae fuit Fagun. quam Robert' filius Ermwi de me tenuit illi &amp; haeredibus ſuis qui de dicta Bertrea filia mea pervenient habend' &amp; tenend' de me &amp; haeredibus meis in feodo &amp; haereditate libere &amp; quiete plene &amp; pacifice in boſco &amp; plano in pratis &amp; paſcuis in aquis viis &amp; in ſemitis in vivariis &amp; in molendinis &amp; in omnibus locis &amp; libertatibus praedictis terris per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentibus ſicut liberum maritagium melius &amp; liberius teneri pot': Et ego &amp; haeredes mei illi &amp; dictis haeredibus ſuis contra omnes homines dictas terras Warrantiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100577:20"/>Teſt' Ran' Com' Ceſtr. Hug' Com' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltoniae, Phil' de Orreby tunc Juſtic. Cestr. Joh. de Ptell' Hug. Malebiſſ. Ric. de Vern. Ran. de Meidnilwar. Clerico. Lidulf. de Tuaml' Rob. de Periis, Ric. de Kingeſt. Norm. Pant. Tho. de Orreby, Alured. de Sulinni. Pet. Chan. Gg. de Aldith. Ric. de Rodeſt. Clerico &amp; multis aliis.</p>
               <p>OMnibus hanc Cartam viſuris vel au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dituris Rogerus de Menilwarin aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam in Domino ſalutem. Noverit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas veſtra me pro ſalute animae Domini Ranulphi quondam Comitis Ceſtriae &amp; Lincolniae Avunculi mei &amp; proſalute ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae meae &amp; animarum anteceſſorum &amp; ſucceſſorum meorum dediſſe conceſſiſſe &amp; hac praeſenti Carta mea confirmaſſe Deo &amp; Beatae Mariae &amp; Abbati &amp; Monachis de Deulacreſſe &amp; eorum Grangie de Biveleg. in liberam puram &amp; perpetuam Elemoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam liberam communam in boſco meo de Pevere, ſcilicet, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t accipiant de eodem boſco husbot &amp; haybot rationabiliter per viſum alicujus foreſtariorum meorum quantum neceſſe habuerint, ſine impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento aeriarum niſorum meorum ubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nidificaverint, Praeterea dedi eis libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100577:20"/>peſſionem &amp; quietam de pannagio quinquaginta porcis quandocunque volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint in praedicto nemore meo de Pevere, pro hac autem donatione &amp; conceſſione mea, Ego Rogerus praedictus &amp; haeredes mei de praedictis Abbate &amp; Monachis de Deulacreſſe nichil exigere poterimus, niſi orationes &amp; ſuffragia ordinis Ciſtercienſis. Ego vero &amp; haeredes mei ſepedictam dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem &amp; conceſſionem meam ſepedictis Abbati &amp; Monachis &amp; Grangie de Bive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg contra omnes gentes Warrantizabimus imperpetuum. Et ut haec donatio mea rata &amp; inconcuſſa in ſempiternum perſeveret eam praeſentis Cartae teſtimonio &amp; Sigilli mei impreſſione roboravi. Hiis teſtibus Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmo de Menilwarin. Willielmo Capellano de Lauton. Ricardo de Moſton. Bened. de Cawdray, Johanne de Motlawe, Willielmo de Pevere, Hugone de Weloc. Nicolao de Wereford, Gilberto Gekell &amp; aliis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>And now I ſhall conſider of your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the firſt Reaſon on the behalf of <hi>Amicia;</hi> which Reaſon, I think, ſhould have been expreſſed to this, or the like effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Common Law neither now doth, nor heretofore ever did allow, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100577:21"/>Lands or Services could be paſſed <hi>In libero Maritagio</hi> with a Baſtard Danghter by the Reputed Father, becauſe a Baſtard is not <hi>De ſanguine Patris.</hi> And therefore <hi>Amicia</hi> having Services given with her <hi>In libero Maritagio</hi> by her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it neceſſarily follows that <hi>Amicia</hi> was no Baſtard.</p>
            <p>To which, your Anſwer is, that it is true, the Law is ſo taken at this day; but you much doubt, whether it was ſo taken in the elder Ages of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and upwards; and to make good what you ſay, you cite my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton</hi> in ſeveral places; as alſo <hi>Glanvile,</hi> Cheif Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> who lived in the ſame time that <hi>Amicia</hi> did; and you alſo alledge, that you have found a Precedent where Lands were given by the Father in Free Marriage with his Baſe Daughter.</p>
            <p>To what you urge out of my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> I do thus ſay, That I do conceive the Common Law, where not altered by Parliament, is the ſame at this day that it was formerly; and therefore my Lord <hi>Coke on Littleton,</hi> telling us <hi>Pag.</hi> 115. <hi>b.</hi> that it is a Maxim of the Law, <hi>That whatſoever was at the Common Law,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100577:21"/>and is not ouſted or taken away by any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, remaineth ſtill.</hi> I might thence argue, That if it had ever been at the Common Law, that a Man might have given Lands or Services <hi>In libero Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio</hi> with a Baſtard, or one that is not of the Blood, that it would be lawful to do ſo ſtill, becauſe that part of the Law is not ouſted, or taken away by any Statute; but a Man cannot do ſo now: And therefore the Common Law never was, that a Man might give Lands or Services with a Baſtard in Free Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or to one that was not of the Blood. So that thoſe places which you have cited, do not prove, That the Common Law at this day doth vary from what it was in former ages in any particular, but onely that it was taken to be otherwiſe in thoſe days; and it is but juſt like ſome Caſes in our <hi>Reports,</hi> which have at ſeveral times been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged directly contrary to each other, but notwithſtanding that, the Law was ſtill the ſame.</p>
            <p>But that I may come as near you as I can, I ſhall acknowledge, that though the Common Law was ever the ſame, where not altered by Parliament, yet in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100577:22"/>Ages they did in ſome particulars, take the Law to be otherwiſe then they now do; and if you could prove, that they did ſo in this Caſe of Free Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, it would take off much of the ſtrength of this Argument, becauſe that Antient Deeds and Grants (according to what my Lord <hi>Coke on Littleton,</hi> ſays <hi>fol.</hi> 8. <hi>b.</hi> at the bottom) are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as the Law was taken to be at the time of the Grant: But this is ſo far from making againſt my opinion, that I think it doth add very much ſtrength thereto; for if it had been taken in former Ages, that Lands might have been given in Free Marriage with a Baſtard, or one not of the Blood, it certainly would ſometime or other, have been ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by ſome of the Sages of the Law; for where the Law hath been taken in one Age after one manner, and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other age after another manner, it is ſo remarkable, that it could not paſs unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by all.</p>
            <p>As to what you alleage out of <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> who ſays, <hi>Quilibet liber homo quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam partem terrae ſuae cum Filia ſua vel cum aliqua alia qualibet muliere dare poteſt in Maritagium.</hi> I do conceive it is the ſame
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100577:22"/>thing in Law, and ſhall be ſo intended, as if it had been expreſly ſaid, <hi>With any Woman of his Kinred;</hi> and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe though ſuch kind of Expreſſions ſeem to be Univerſal, and without any exception at all; yet they ſhall not be ſo largely taken, but ſhall be expounded ſo as may agree with the Laws of that Kingdom or Nation, to which they particularly do relate; and for this I ſhall give you an example out of Scripture it ſelf. In the Fourteenth Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſixth Verſe, there was a Liberty given to the <hi>Jews</hi> in ſome Caſes, and at ſome of their Feaſts, to eat <hi>whatſoever their Soul luſted after, and whatſoever their Soul deſired:</hi> And yet this was not to be expounded univerſally of all Meats whatſoever (in caſe they deſired the ſame) but muſt be meant onely of ſuch Meats as were legally clean, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to eat by their Law. And thus, when we alſo ſay, That any Man that hath Money enough, may buy Lands when he pleaſeth, it ſhall not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of any Man whatſoever: For, a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100577:23"/>Traytor, or a <hi>Jew,</hi> or one that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of Felony, or an Alien cannot purchaſe Land in <hi>England;</hi> but it ſhall be underſtood of one that is by Law enabled ſo to do: And ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the words <hi>Cum alia qualibet muliere,</hi> muſt be underſtood onely of ſuch a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as is capable of ſuch a gift, which a Woman that is a Baſtard, or not of the Blood, or a Jew, or an Alien, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is not. For in theſe kind of Gifts, as Mr. <hi>Bracton</hi> tells you, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. the Land ſo given is <hi>Liberum tenementum uxoris, &amp; non viri, cum non habeat niſi cuſtodiam cum uxore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe I do conceive that <hi>Glanvil</hi> hath immediately contradicted himſelf, unleſs by theſe words, <hi>Cum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liqua alia qualibet muliere,</hi> he underſtands a Woman that is of the Blood of the Donor: For he tells us in the ſame Chapter, and the very next words to thoſe that you cite, That none can give Lands <hi>in remunerationem ſervitii ſui,</hi> to hold good after the death of the Donor, unleſs there be Seiſin in the life time of the Donor, which is untrue. If a Man having a mind ſo to reward his Servants, can give Lands with his Woman-ſervant
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100577:23"/>to a ſtranger, or with his Woman-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to his Man-ſervant in Free Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. For, where Lands are given <hi>In libero Maritagio,</hi> according to Law, there needs no Seiſin; and where they are given contrary to the Law, <hi>viz.</hi> (to one not of the Blood of the Donor) Seiſin doth onely make it an Eſtate for Life, as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſays in his <hi>Inſtitutes, Part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> So that it ſeems clear, <hi>Glanvil</hi> by the words <hi>Cum aliqua alia qualibet muliere,</hi> underſtands one of the Blood of the Donor, as well as I hope hereafter to prove that <hi>Bracton</hi> doth by the words <hi>Cum aliqua muliere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe that though <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. ſays, A Man may give part of his Heritage to his Baſtard; and that alſo <hi>Bracton</hi> in his Second Book, and beginning of his Seventh Chapter tells us, That Lands may be given <hi>Bastardo in Maritagium cum aliqua muliere;</hi> yet neither of them hath one word at all to prove, That Lands may be given to a Man <hi>cum Baſtarda,</hi> whereas in this Caſe of Frank-marriage, the party <hi>with whom</hi> the Land is given, not the party <hi>to whom</hi> the Land is given, is the principal thing that is conſiderable herein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100577:24"/>Fourthly, Becauſe my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Part of his Inſtitutes, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> tells us, That if the King give Land to a Man with a Woman of his Kinred in Frank-marriage, and the Woman dieth without Iſſue, the Man in the Kings Caſe ſhall not hold it for his life, becauſe the Woman was the cauſe of the Gift; but it is otherwiſe in the Caſe of a common Perſon. And to prove this, in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent he cites, 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Dower</hi> 202. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if you look <hi>Fitz-Herberts Graund Abridgment,</hi> 9 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>Dower.</hi> 202. the words run thus, <hi>Si le Roy donne certeine tre a un homme ove une feme en mariage, ſi le bar' nad iſſue pur la feme il naver la tre apres la morte la feme mes ceſt iſſu q' la feme au devaunt enherit, &amp;c.</hi> So that you ſee in theſe Caſes of Free Marriage, my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> makes no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between theſe words, <hi>Ove une feme,</hi> and theſe words, <hi>With a Woman of his Kinred;</hi> and by the ſame Reaſon, being in the Caſe of Frank-marriage al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Glanvile</hi>'s words, <hi>Cum alia qualibet muliere,</hi> are to be underſtood, with any other Woman <hi>of his Kinred onely.</hi> Alſo, which is very obſervable, <hi>Glanvile</hi> was firſt made Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> 26 <hi>Hen.</hi> 2.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100577:24"/>as Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> tells you in his Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of <hi>Lord Chancellors, Lord Keepers, Lord Treaſurers, Juſtices, &amp;c.</hi> which was about Forty five years before the 9 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. Therefore what likelihood is there, that the Law ſhould be different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken in ſo ſhort a time, from what it was in the time of <hi>Glanvile,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince the Statute of <hi>Westminster,</hi> the Second, was not made till about Threeſcore years after the Nineth of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Becauſe the Author of the Book called <hi>The Laws Reſolutions of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Rights,</hi> Printed by the Aſſigns of <hi>John More,</hi> 1632. doth tell us, That in old time theſe Gifts in Frank-marriage were to be made to them of the Kinred, as well as now. His words in his Thirty third Section of <hi>Frank-marriage, pag.</hi> 73. are theſe. <hi>It was, as I ſuppoſe,</hi> more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the old time, that Men gave Lands with their Daughters in Marriage, then it was at this day; but now as then if a Man liberally and freely, without any Money or other conſiderations, ſave onely Love and Natural Affection, give Lands or Tenements to another Man, with a Woman which is a Daughter,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100577:25"/>Siſter, or Coſin to the Donor in Frank-marriage, whether it be <hi>tempore Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii, vel ante, vel poſt.</hi> This word Frank-marriage maketh an Eſtate of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, <hi>viz.</hi> to the Donees, and the Heirs of their Two Bodies, and they ſhall hold quite of all manner of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices (except the pure Fealty) till the Fourth degree be paſt; but the Iſſue in the Fifth degree, and his Deſcendant, ſhall hold of the Donor and his Heirs, as they hold over.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Becauſe the Author of the old Treatiſe, commonly called <hi>Fleta,</hi> in the Third Book, and Eleventh Chapter, <hi>De donationibus in Maritagiis,</hi> doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that theſe kind of Gifts muſt be made to them <hi>of the Kinred;</hi> his very words are theſe, <hi>Eſt autem quoddam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagium liberum ab omni ſervitio ſolutum donatori, vel ejus haeredibus uſque ad ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium haeredem vel uſque ad quartum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum faciendum &amp; debent gradus ſic com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putari, ut Donatorius primum faciat gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, haeres ejus ſecundum gradum, haeres haeredis tertium, &amp; haeres ſecundi haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis quartum, qui quidem tenebitur ad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium ut ad homagium, prius autem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime ne Donator vel ejus haeredes per homa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100577:25"/>homagii acceptionem a reverſione repellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed in quarto gradu pro eo quod tune vehementer preſumitur quod terra non est pro defectu haeredum donatoriarum rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura, quia etſi propinquos haeredes non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, vel cum habeat &amp; defecerint ad do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorem vel ejus haeredes qui homagium ceperint non erit terra reverſura, dum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aliquis remotus</hi> de conſanguinitate <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareat, qui jus in haereditatem poterit ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicare alioquin evaneſcit homagium, &amp; revertetur. Et cum</hi> de ſanguine <hi>homagium factum fuerit, extunc obligatur homo ad ſervitium, quia ſervitium ſemper ſequitur homagium, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, Becauſe <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>par.</hi> 3. ſays thus, <hi>Et ſciendum quod terra datur aliquando ante ſponſalia &amp; propter nuptias a patre mulieris vel alio parente ipſi marito</hi> cum muliere aliqua <hi>vel utrique ſimul, ſc. tali viro &amp; uxori ſuae (quod idem eſt) &amp; eorum haeredibus vel alicui mulieri ad ſe maritandam, &amp;c.</hi> And preſently after, <hi>Fit etiam talis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio ante Matrimonium contractum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando in ipſo contractu, aliquando poſt contractum.</hi> Which in my apprehenſion is as much as to ſay, That this kind of Gift can onely be made by the Father,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100577:26"/>Mother, or ſome other Kinſman, (for the word <hi>parens</hi> or <hi>parent</hi> in Latine and French hath oftentimes that ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) and of this opinion was my Lord <hi>Coke.</hi> For in his <hi>Inſtitutes upon Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, pag.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> he tells you, That one of thoſe things incident to a Frank-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is, that the Woman that is the cauſe of the Gift, be of the Blood of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and for this as appears Letter (1) amongſt other Proofs, he in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cites <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. Alſo, which is very conſiderable, Mr. <hi>Bracton</hi> here uſeth this expreſſion <hi>Cum muliere aliqua,</hi> and yet meaneth a Kinſwoman, and why then ſhould we think that Mr. <hi>Glanvile</hi> doth not mean a Kinſwoman, though he uſe this expreſſion <hi>Cum alia qualibet muliere,</hi> and eſpecially ſince my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in the very Page of his <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> laſt mentioned, quotes Mr. <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. And amongſt others, that expreſſion of his <hi>Cum aliqua muliere in Maritagium;</hi> and alſo in the Margent cites <hi>Glanvile, lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. (the very place on which you frame your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) which he would never have done, if he had thought the opinion of <hi>Glanvile</hi> had been contradictory to his
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100577:26"/>own. And if there had been any ſuch thing, as that the Law in this point had been ſeverally taken in ſo very ſhort a ſpace, as betwixt the time of <hi>Bracton</hi> and <hi>Glanvile,</hi> ſure my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> would in that place have taken notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Eightly, and laſtly, The Law appears to be the ſame in this Caſe which it was in <hi>Glanvile</hi>'s time, becauſe as <hi>Littleton</hi> tells us in his 271 <hi>Section,</hi> Gifts in Free-marriage were by the Common Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. Now the Common Law hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been the ſame, and as my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> tells us in his Firſt Part of <hi>Inſtitutes, fol.</hi> 115. <hi>b.</hi> hath no Controuler in any part of it, but the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and if it be not abrogated or altered by Parliament it remains ſtill: But the Parliament hath made no altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning Gifts in Free-marriage, except the ſaid Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Second, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. By which they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Eſtate that paſſed by thoſe Gifts in Feeſimple into an Eſtate Tail, (all Inheritances being Feeſimple before the ſaid Statute) ſo that in other reſpects the Law in this Caſe remains as it did.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100577:27"/>And that this is ſo, I conceive is very clear, becauſe, I ſuppoſe neither you, nor any other perſon, can tell any one particular in which the Common Law is, or hath been altered but by Act of Parliament: Neither could there be any occaſion to alter the Common Law, or to take it otherways in this particular then they did formerly, becauſe ſince there were Eſtates in Tail, there could be no great occaſion to make Gifts in Free-marriages; and therefore my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſays in his Firſt Part of <hi>Inſtitutes, fol.</hi> 178. <hi>b.</hi> That ſuch Gifts are almoſt grown out of uſe, and ſerve now prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally for Moot Caſes and Queſtions in the Law, that thereupon were wont to ariſe.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any weight in what you ſay, That it ſeems to you, that in thoſe elder Ages Baſtards were reputed of the Blood, by the frequent appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them by the names of Uncle, Brother, Daughter, Son, and Coſin; for, by the ſame Reaſon you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them of the Blood now, this Age being as civil to them in their expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as any former Age could poſſibly be.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100577:27"/>And for the Precedent you give me, wherein you ſay Lands were given <hi>in libero maritagio</hi> with a Baſtard, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it will not hold;</p>
            <p>Becauſe it doth not certainly appear, that <hi>Geva</hi> was a Baſtard; for, in all the <hi>Records</hi> that you cite, ſhe is called Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Daughter; and in one of them, ſhe calls <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> her Coſin, which makes it probable that ſhe was <hi>Legitimate,</hi> eſpecially, ſince I do not find by any <hi>Deed, Record,</hi> or <hi>Author</hi> whatſoever, that ſhe is at any time cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Baſtard.</p>
            <p>As for your ſaying, That it is plain out of <hi>Ordericus, p.</hi> 787. that <hi>Geva</hi> was a Baſtard, becauſe, ſpeaking of <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> his death, he adds theſe words, <hi>Richardus autem pulcherrimus puer quem ſolum ex Ementrude Filia Hugonis de Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romonte genuit.</hi> I am not ſatisfied, but he might as well mean, that he was the <hi>onely Son</hi> which Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had by <hi>Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude,</hi> as that he was the <hi>onely Child</hi> that he had by her. For, there is no neceſſity to take the word <hi>Solum adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bially;</hi> neither is it marked as an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb</hi> in <hi>Ordericus</hi> his Book, though it be ſo in yours, and yet in his Book <hi>Adverbs</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100577:28"/>are uſually marked. And though that <hi>Ordericus</hi> (if his meaning were ſo) might have worded it more clearly, yet he many times expreſſeth himſelf worſe then he doth here, and particularly <hi>Pag.</hi> 871. And though he tells us, <hi>Pag.</hi> 522. that <hi>E pellicibus plurimam ſobolem utriuſque ſexus genuit;</hi> yet he doth not ſay that <hi>Geva</hi> was one of them.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any force in what you alledge, that probably if <hi>Hugh Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> had any more <hi>Legitimate Children</hi> by his Wife beſides Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> either Son or Daughter, that <hi>Ordericus</hi> would have Recorded them as well as others, being indeed his uſual method through the whole courſe of his Hiſtory. For he could have no <hi>Legitimate Son</hi> but Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> unleſs he had another Wife beſides <hi>Ementrude</hi> (<hi>Ordericus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expreſs therein) and poſſibly for ſome Reaſons he might have another Wife beſides <hi>Ementrude:</hi> But whether <hi>Geva</hi> was by a Firſt or ſecond Wife, I know no neceſſity to conclude that <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericus</hi> ſhould Record her, I finding no ſuch uſual method of his, as this which you ſpeak of: For he doth not (that I ſee) make it his buſineſs to Record what
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100577:28"/>Wives or Children the Earls of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and other great Men had, but onely ſpeaks of them occaſionally, and ſo he alſo doth of ſome of their <hi>Illegitimate Children;</hi> but if he made it his deſign to give an exact account of theſe things, he ought to reckon <hi>Geva,</hi> either amongſt the lawful, doubtful, or illegitimate Children of <hi>Hugh Lupus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to your Objection, That if <hi>Geva</hi> had been Legitimate, her Iſſue ought rather to have ſucceeded into the Earldom of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> then <hi>Randle de Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chines,</hi> after the death of <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> That doth not at all follow, becauſe, it is poſſible the Earldom of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> at that time (as moſt times Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms anciently were) might be Entail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Heirs-males onely, and then the Male Line being extinct, why might not the King confer it as well upon <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle de Meſchines,</hi> who was a near Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as upon a ſtranger? Which later courſe is alſo uſual at this day. And it is very probable, that the Earldom was Entailed on the Heirs-males onely; for <hi>James York</hi> in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Honor, p.</hi> 105. ſays, That this <hi>Randle</hi> was made Earl by Grant of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100577:29"/>if ſo, it came not to him by Deſcent: So that all which you here object is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered. But if it had been ſo, that the Earldom had been to Deſcend to the Heirs General; if <hi>Geva</hi> was Daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> by another Wife, beſides <hi>Ementrude;</hi> then the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Cheſter</hi> would have Deſcended from Earl <hi>Richard</hi> to <hi>Randle Meſchines</hi> by his Mother, being Aunt of the whole Blood to <hi>Richard,</hi> and not to his Siſter <hi>Geva,</hi> or her Iſſue, they being but of the Half Blood to him.</p>
            <p>And whereas you deſire me to ſhew you a Precedent where-ever the Heirs of an Aunt inherited, before the Heirs of a Siſter, both legally born, and no Heirs-male left, unleſs in Caſe of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture by Treaſon, or ſome other great cauſe to hinder the ſame. I ſhall now ſhew you where an <hi>Honor</hi> in ſuch a Caſe came to the Heirs of the younger Siſter, and not to the Heirs of the elder Siſter, which is full as much as if it were done in the Caſe of a Siſter and an Aunt. If you peruſe the <hi>Magazin of Honor,</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Mr. <hi>Bird,</hi> and inlarged by Sir <hi>John Doderidge,</hi> One of His Majeſties Juſtices of the <hi>Kings Bench, pag.</hi> 96. you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100577:29"/>will there find, That whereas <hi>Radulfe,</hi> Lord <hi>Cromwel,</hi> being a Baron by Writ, died without Iſſue, having Two Siſters, and Coheirs, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Eldeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Sir <hi>Thomas Nevil,</hi> and <hi>Joan</hi> the Younger married to Sir <hi>Hunt Bourcher:</hi> He who had married the Younger Siſter, was called to the Parliament as Lord <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and not the ſaid Sir <hi>Tho. Nevil,</hi> who had married the Elder Siſter; ſo that you ſee no convincing Argument can be brought from the enjoyment of the Earldom by <hi>Randle de Meſchines,</hi> however the Caſe prove to be.</p>
            <p>I do therefore ſtill conceive, That it is very clear that Lands or Services never were in any Age paſſed, <hi>In libero Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio</hi> with a Baſtard, or with any one that was not of the Blood, but onely for Term of Life, and that with Livery and Seiſin; and conſequently, all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom ſuch <hi>Deeds</hi> or <hi>Grants</hi> were made (unleſs for life only) are certainly to be concluded <hi>Legitimate;</hi> and if you will bring a <hi>Convincing Precedent</hi> to the contrary, do not produce a <hi>Record</hi> or <hi>Deed</hi> of Lands or Services given with one that you ſuppoſe to be a Baſtard, or not of the Blood; but firſt clearly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100577:30"/>prove, That the party was certainly a Baſtard, or not of the Blood, by ſome <hi>Deed, Record,</hi> or <hi>Ancient History,</hi> and ſhew Lands or Services ſo given with her and then there will be ſome ſtrength in ſuch a Precedent.</p>
            <p>But what will you ſay, If this <hi>Deed</hi> which you alledge to be made to <hi>Geva,</hi> will not at all concern <hi>Amicia,</hi> if <hi>Geva</hi> were a Baſtard. If you peruſe what my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> ſays <hi>pag.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> he will there tell you, That theſe words <hi>In liberum Maritagium,</hi> are ſuch words of art, and ſo neceſſarily required, as they cannot be expreſſed by words equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollent, or amounting to as much. As if a Man give Lands to another with his Daughter <hi>In connubio ſoluto ab omni ſervitio, &amp;c.</hi> yet there paſſeth in this Caſe but an Eſtate for Life; for ſeeing that theſe words <hi>In liberum Maritagium</hi> create an Eſtate of Inheritance againſt the general Rule of Law, the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that they ſhould be legally pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued. And in this Deed to <hi>Geva,</hi> the words are not <hi>In liberum Maritagium,</hi> but <hi>In libero Conjugio;</hi> and ſo are but like the words <hi>In connubio ſoluto ab omni ſervitio,</hi> which make but an Eſtate for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100577:30"/>Life, and ſo might be paſſed either to a Baſtard, or any other perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And if you look well on the Deed to <hi>Geva,</hi> it is worded as if it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended onely an Eſtate for Life, there being no mention of her Heirs, and running alſo in the ſingular number, <hi>Et teneat bene &amp; in pace, &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t melius &amp; liberius tenuit, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo, if you obſerve my Lord <hi>Coke upon Littleton,</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the ſame <hi>Page,</hi> he will tell you, that Four things are incident to a Frank-marriage: The firſt whereof is, That it be given for conſideration of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, either to a Man with a Woman, or as ſome have held, to a Woman with a Man, (and with this <hi>Bracton, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. doth accord.) And the fourth thing is, That the <hi>Donees</hi> ſhall hold freely of the <hi>Donor,</hi> till the fourth degree be paſt, (with which the old. Treatiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Fleta, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. doth agree.) For both which Reaſons, this Gift can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a Gift in Frank-marriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, what is here given, is given to <hi>Geva</hi> alone, and not to an Husband with her; as alſo, there are here <hi>no Donees,</hi> but <hi>one Donee</hi> onely, and the Eſtate was not to continue until the fourth degree
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100577:31"/>was paſt, but was onely an Eſtate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the Life of <hi>Geva,</hi> as appears before; whereas what was given by Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> to <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Amicia,</hi> and by <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> to <hi>Henry de Alditelegh</hi> with his Daughter <hi>Bertred,</hi> was given in Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage, and their Heirs are mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both the <hi>Deeds:</hi> It remains there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore clear, That the Deed to <hi>Geva</hi> was not a Gift in Frank-marriage, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo very uncertain, whether <hi>Geva</hi> was a Baſtard, as you ſuppoſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Reaſon alledged to prove, That <hi>Amicia</hi> was Legitimate, hath alſo yet its full ſtrength, and is not at all weakned by any thing that you have ſaid: For, I think it will ſtill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was much Elder then his Wife <hi>Bertred;</hi> and therefore probably had a former Wife, who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and leaving him no Iſſue-male, it is no wonder at all, if he that had ſo great an Eſtate, did afterwards marry a Lady that was very much younger than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And though you do affirm, That Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> could not be above Seven or eight years older then <hi>Bertred</hi> his Wife, I ſuppoſe I ſhall make it appear, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100577:31"/>there might be many more years betwixt them, and that from the Argument up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you your ſelf do reckon, <hi>viz.</hi> The Marriage of <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> with <hi>Mabill</hi> Daughter and Heir of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Fitz-Haimon.</hi> For whether the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> according to <hi>Selden,</hi> married the ſaid <hi>Mabill</hi> in the year 1109. or according to <hi>Stow</hi> in the year 1110. The ſaid <hi>Mabill</hi> might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly have <hi>Maud,</hi> her ſecond Daughter in the year 1112. Which <hi>Maud,</hi> if ſhe was married in the year 1128. when ſhe was Sixteen years of Age to Earl <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> might have her Son <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> in the year 1129. Which if true, the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was Fifty two years of age at his death, for he died in the year 1181. And if ſo, then he was four years above twice the age of <hi>Bertred;</hi> for ſhe was aged but Twenty four years when the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> died, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <hi>Rot. de Dominabus pueris, &amp;c. In Scacc. penes Remem. R. ſub Tit. Linc. Rot.</hi> 1. And it is certain, That the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> was Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> about four years before his Wife <hi>Bertred</hi> was born, beſides what age he was of, when his Father died: But I may very well abate
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100577:32"/>you ſeveral years of this accompt, and yet Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> be a great deal older then his Wife <hi>Bertred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to the Third and fourth Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they were onely urged as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current Proof, with the Argument brought from the words <hi>In libero Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio,</hi> yet I conceive there are many more circumſtances than you take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of: And therefore when I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them all, <hi>viz.</hi> That in the firſt Deed, <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>'s Counteſs is a <hi>Witneſs,</hi> by which the ſaid Earl gives Services to the ſaid <hi>Amicia</hi> in Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage, and calls her his Daughter: And in the ſecond, That <hi>Ralph Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warings</hi> Daughter is alſo called <hi>Bertred</hi> after the Counteſs, and <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> a <hi>Witneſs</hi> to what was given with her in Free-marriage to <hi>Henry de Aldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telegh,</hi> who was Great Grand-father to the Famous <hi>James Audley</hi> that warred in <hi>France.</hi> And in the third, How <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> in his Gift to the Monks of <hi>Deulacreſs,</hi> calls <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln</hi> his Uncle; and how, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s <hi>Antiquities of Warwickſhire, pag.</hi> 88. <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> was with the ſaid Earl at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100577:32"/>
               <hi>Witneſs</hi> to his Charter to his Burgeſſes there; as alſo, how <hi>Roger de Meinwarin</hi> and <hi>Henry de Aldithele,</hi> who married his Siſter, <hi>Monaſt. Angl. Part</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 891. are <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to the Deed of <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Lincoln,</hi> concerning his Abbey of <hi>Deulacreſs;</hi> as alſo, how the ſaid <hi>Henry de Audley, Monaſtic. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 509. was a <hi>Witneſs</hi> to the Deed of <hi>Robert de Ferraris,</hi> whoſe Mother was one of the Siſters and Coheirs to the aforeſaid Earl <hi>Randle;</hi> as alſo, how <hi>Raph Menilwaringe</hi> or <hi>Mainwaring,</hi> as appears by your Book, <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 130. 131. 139. 143. and 144. is a <hi>Witneſs</hi> to one Deed of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks,</hi> and to three other Deeds of the ſaid Earl <hi>Randle,</hi> (who in ſome of them is alſo ſtiled Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> and Earl of <hi>Richmond</hi>) I ſhall leave it (without any more words) to the Reader to judge, whether theſe Circumſtances be not ſuch as do ſhew more great and conſtant intimacy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſaid Two Families, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably would have been, if <hi>Amice</hi> had been a Baſtard; and if ſo, they ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concur to prove her Legitimate, which is all the uſe that is made of thoſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100577:33"/>And although you Object, That you frequently find in <hi>Histories</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> that <hi>Baſtards</hi> are called Coſin, Brother, Uncle, Son, and Daughter. I grant it to be true, yet that is either done where the perſons came to be very great, as <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> did, or elſe, are called ſo by thoſe that write the Hiſtories of them, or elſe are ſo termed by their Relations, who out of their Humility did condeſcend ſo to ſtile them upon ordinary occaſions, though it were not their due. But I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you can hardly find one that you can certainly prove to be a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> or the Son of a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> who doth preſume in a <hi>Deed</hi> to call ſo great a perſon, as the Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> was, his Brother, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, unleſs he came to be a very great perſon himſelf.</p>
            <p>Alſo I do verily believe, that <hi>Richard Bacun</hi>'s Mother was not a Baſe Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Cyvelioks,</hi> nor any Daughter of his at all, becauſe, as you may ſee <hi>Monaſt. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 267. When <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> did found the Priory of <hi>Rouceſter</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> his Uncle <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> was then living, and a <hi>William</hi> was then Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:100577:33"/>and one whoſe name did begin with <hi>R.</hi> was then Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> but if the Catalogue of Archbiſhops and Biſhops at the end of <hi>Iſaackson</hi>'s Chronology be right, there was no <hi>William</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> during the life of <hi>Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devile;</hi> nor any Man Biſhop of <hi>Chester,</hi> whoſe Chriſtian name began with <hi>R.</hi> except <hi>Richard Peche,</hi> who died in the year 1182. At which time <hi>Randle Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devile</hi> could not be of age to Seal any kind of Deed, becauſe <hi>Bertred,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Randle</hi>'s Mother, was then but about Twenty five years of age. I rather think that <hi>Bacun</hi>'s Uncle, mentioned <hi>Monaſtic. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 267. was <hi>Randle de Gernoniis;</hi> for he was Earl from the year 1128. to about the year 1152. And in the year 1143. as <hi>Iſaack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſays, <hi>William</hi> Siſters Son to King <hi>Stephen,</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> but was ouſted of it again, till about 1152. or 1153. And <hi>Roger Clinton</hi> from the year 1128. until the year 1149. was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Leichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry;</hi> which Biſhop in elder ages, was the ſame with the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> But that <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who is mentioned <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſt. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 268. was indeed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100577:34"/>
               <hi>Randle Blundevile,</hi> who was Earl from about the year 1180. till about the year 1232. (<hi>Roger Conſtable</hi> of <hi>Chester,</hi> who lived in the time of no other Earl <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle,</hi> being a Witneſs to the ſaid Deed) But what the ſaid <hi>Randle Blundevile</hi> did, was but by way of Confirmation, which in former times was very uſual to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from Princes ſeveral Generations after; as to inſtance in one Caſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of many. If you read <hi>Monaſtic. Angl. Part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 24 <hi>&amp;</hi> 25. you will find King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, Reciting and Confirming what had been given to the Priory of <hi>Huntendune,</hi> and <hi>Pag.</hi> 27. you may find King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third doing the like; and yet there was a greater ſpace betwixt King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, and King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, than there was betwixt <hi>Randle de Gernoniis</hi> and <hi>Randle Blundevile.</hi> So that you may ſee, ſuch great perſons as theſe may have ſome Children which our Hiſtorians take no notice of: And you may alſo diſcover upon what ſlender Grounds you have charged <hi>Richard Bacun</hi>'s Mother with Baſtardy, ſhe being ſo far from being a Baſe Daughter to <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> that ſhe was no Daughter of his at all; but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100577:34"/>ſhe was Siſter to <hi>Randle de Gernoniis,</hi> and Daughter to <hi>Randle Meſchines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall now come to Anſwer the Reaſons that you bring to prove, That <hi>Amice</hi> was a Baſtard. And your firſt is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>had no other Wife but</hi> Bertred, <hi>then</hi> Amice <hi>muſt be certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Baſtard; for ſhe was not a Daughter by</hi> Bertred <hi>as is granted on all fides: But</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>never had any other Wife but</hi> Bertred. Ergo, Amice <hi>was a Baſtard. And you ſay the Minor is to be proved by the Affirmer; For,</hi> Oportet Affirmantem probare.</p>
            <p>To this I ſay,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That by this Rule you your ſelf are as much bound to prove her a Baſtard, as I am bound to prove that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had a former Wife; for you as clearly affirm that, as I affirm the other; and there is no reaſon why Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſhould paſs for Proofs any more in your Caſe, then they ſhould do in mine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That leſs Proof by many degrees will ſerve to prove a thing that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100577:35"/>was done long ſince, then will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to prove that which was done late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. To inſtance in one Caſe, which may ſerve inſtead of many: If you be to prove a Deed that was lately Sealed, it will be expected you produce the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes who were preſent at the Sealing and Delivery thereof. If your Deed was ſealed a good while ago, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Hands will be required: But if the Deed be ſo old, that none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live could know the Hand-writing of the Witneſſes, then the Deed carries its own Proof with it: And the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there is in all Caſes of Antiquity, and eſpecially in thoſe that are ſo very ancient as this is. For, if I did onely prove her called a Daughter, being it is ſo long ſince, ſhe ought to be preſumed Legitimate, unleſs the contrary do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. For the proving ſhe was not by <hi>Bertred,</hi> does not prove that ſhe was a Baſtard; but onely proves that ſhe was either a Baſtard, or elſe by a former Wife: And our Law at this day is, That a Baſtard cannot be proved a Baſtard but in his life time; and ſo it anciently was alſo, as appears by the Old Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe called <hi>Fleta, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 39. <hi>ſect.</hi> 14.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100577:35"/>where it is thus ſaid, <hi>Si autem poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem alicujus apponatur Baſtardia, non allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabitur; cum defunctus ad talem exceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem reſpondere non poterit.</hi> Now, if a Perſon cannot be proved a Baſtard im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after his death, becauſe he cannot anſwer for himſelf, What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there to charge <hi>Amice</hi> with Baſtardy ſo many hundred years after her deceaſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I do conceive that the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Services <hi>In libero Maritagio</hi> with <hi>Amice,</hi> doth abſolutely prove that ſhe was a lawful Child, and by conſequence by a former Wife: Alſo, if you take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> writes in his <hi>Gloſſary,</hi> on the word <hi>Baſtardus,</hi> you will find him quoting <hi>Couſtum. du Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Artic.</hi> 77. <hi>in Annot.</hi> thus, <hi>Quoties enim agitur de honore vel commodo Filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, appellatione Filiorum non compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henduntur Baſtardi.</hi> I ſuppoſe therefore in this Caſe, <hi>Amice</hi> would not have been ſtiled as ſhe is in the ſaid Deed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe had been a Legitimate Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If this Argument of yours would hold as you have framed it, we ſhould have almoſt nothing but Baſtards
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100577:36"/>in the Ancient times: For if all muſt be Baſtards, if we could not tell who their Mothers were, nor directly prove their Fathers married, we might then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, moſt perſons to be Baſtards that lived in the Firſt and ſecond Centuries after the Conqueſt. I ſhall not offer to put the Caſe upon any other Family but my own (though it doth reach a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of others.) But as to my own, if I miſtake not, I find Eight perſons whoſe Wives we are altogether ignorant of, and Six of thoſe perſons left Iſſue, all which Iſſue, by your Argument would be Baſtards; which I am confident you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor will not ſuppoſe. I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance onely in one, <hi>viz. Roger Melin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarin</hi> who in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, as you may ſee in the Firſt Part of <hi>Monaſticon Anglicanum, p.</hi> 985. gave <hi>Plumley</hi> (a place in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> near to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over</hi>) to the Abbey of S. <hi>Werburge</hi> at <hi>Cheſter;</hi> and as it appears by the ſaid Record; the ſaid <hi>Roger Mainwaring</hi> had Three Sons, <hi>William, Randle,</hi> and <hi>Wido.</hi> Now if you ſhould affirm, That the ſaid <hi>William Randle</hi> and <hi>Wido,</hi> were Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, which I verily believe you will not ſcruple to do, I could thus frame
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100577:36"/>your own Argument againſt you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> Roger Melinguarin <hi>had no Wife, then,</hi> William, Randle, <hi>and</hi> Wido, <hi>Sons of the ſaid</hi> Roger <hi>were certainly Baſtards: But</hi> Roger Melinguarin <hi>aforeſaid had no Wife.</hi> Ergo, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now if this Argument would hold againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> it would alſo hold againſt theſe three Children of <hi>Roger Mainwaring,</hi> and indeed againſt all other perſons whoſe Fathers we could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and <hi>interminis</hi> prove to have been married (the Proof lying on the Affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſide) the Abſurdity of which is ſo great, that you your ſelf cry, <hi>God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid all Children ſhould be concluded Baſtards, whoſe Mothers cannot be proved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if it be poſſible for a Man to have one Wife, and we not know who ſhe was, Why may not a Man have two Wives, &amp; we be ignorant who the former Wife was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea, but</hi> (ſay you) <hi>in this Caſe we find a Wife certainly Recorded, and a Son and Four Daughters, who were afterwards Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs, and carried away all Earl</hi> Hugh<hi>'s Lands, clearly proved by Records and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Historians; and alſo Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>is certainly known to have many Baſtards, which gives occaſion of ſtrong ſuſpition that</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100577:37"/>Amice <hi>was a Baſtard; and therefore here is a neceſſity of proving a former Wife, which you firmly believe Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>never had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For anſwer hereunto, I ſay that I do believe if <hi>Randle Blundevile</hi> had left any Iſſue Male, you had not met with ſuch Proof of the Four Siſters his Coheirs, as you now do: For, the falling of that great Eſtate to them, they being of the whole Blood to their Brother, is the occaſion of their being Recorded, and ſo much taken notice of by Hiſtorians. And though this Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> their Father had ſome Iſſue that was not lawful, (as many of the great perſons of that age had,) yet that hinders not but he might have two Wives; neither had he ſo many Baſtards as you lay upon him, for, I have ſhewed before, That <hi>Richard Bacun</hi>'s Mother was not any Child of his: And I do conceive I have by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence proved, That the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had a Wife, who was Mother to <hi>Amicia,</hi> though we cannot tell who ſhe was. And it is no great wonder, if the old Hiſtorians do not mention who <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi>'s firſt Wife was, for, there is not any of the Antient Writers that I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100577:37"/>know of, who doth make it his buſineſs to tell what Wives and Children this Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had; nay, I think there is no Antient Hiſtorian that doth mention his Wife <hi>Bertred:</hi> And therefore, we had never known who ſhe had been, but onely becauſe ſhe ſurvived her Husband, and was mentioned in the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> taken after his death, and becauſe her Daughters after the death of their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came to be Heirs.</p>
            <p>Alſo, it is very hard to tell who were Wives to <hi>Walter Gifford,</hi> the Firſt Earl of <hi>Buckingham; John</hi> of <hi>Henault,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cambridge; Baldwin de Ripariis,</hi> Earl of <hi>Devonſhire; William Fitz-Piers,</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex; Robert de Ferrars,</hi> the Firſt Earl of <hi>Ferrars,</hi> (and as ſome ſay of <hi>Derby</hi>) <hi>Robert de Ferrars,</hi> Second Earl of <hi>Ferrars; Ralph de Maunt,</hi> Earl of <hi>Hereford; Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam de Iper,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent; William de Romara,</hi> Earl of <hi>Lincoln; Morchar,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland; Goſpatrick,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland; Robert Mowbray,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and ſeveral others; and therefore, what great wonder would it be for <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> to have a former Wife, and yet we to be ignorant who that former Wife was.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:100577:38"/>Your ſecond Reaſon againſt <hi>Amicia</hi> will not hold, For though what is given in Frank-marriage, be given in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Marriage, yet it cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called a <hi>Portion.</hi> For, ſuch Gifts may be made either before Marriage, at Marriage, or after Marriage, as you may ſee <hi>Coke on Littl.</hi> 21. <hi>b.</hi> And beſides, what is given as a Portion remaineth to the Husband for ever, and is wholly at his diſpoſal; but Lands given in Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriage, ſhall after the death of the Husband and Wife (if they die without Iſſue) revert to the Donor: Alſo any perſon that pleaſeth may give a Woman a Portion, but none but one of the <hi>whole Blood</hi> can give Lands with a Woman in Frank-marriage, as Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> ſays in his <hi>Grand Abrigdment of the Law, pag.</hi> 970.</p>
            <p>But the reaſon why you call it a <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is, Becauſe you would have it thought that this was all her Portion, and thence would infer, that ſhe was Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate, becauſe ſo very little was given with her: But I think any Man that will weigh things indifferently wil eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That if ſhe had been but a Baſtard, yet being a Baſtard of ſo great a perſon,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100577:38"/>ſhe would have had a great deal more given her then theſe Services, upon thoſe terms that they were given, and eſpecially conſidering how you have obſerved out of Sir <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> that Baſtards were not in ſuch diſrepute in thoſe former ages, as they are now; and beſides, I have made it appear, that Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> was no inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſon, and therefore would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a great deal more. And you may alſo find in one of the Deeds before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, that though the ſaid Sir <hi>Ralph</hi> had Iſſue Male, yet he gave that which was of far greater value in Free-marriage with a Daughter of his own: But I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if this Deed of Earl <hi>Hughes</hi> had been loſt, you would not have believed that Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> had had any thing with <hi>Amicia,</hi> becauſe then it would not have appeared, which is a ſtrange way of arguing, about things that were done ſo long ſince. And, if this be a good reaſon, I wonder you do believe that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had any Portion with his Counteſs <hi>Bertred,</hi> becauſe (for ought I yet know) it doth not appear that he had.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100577:39"/>As for your alleadging how the other Four Siſters were married, I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that before; and though you ſay, That if <hi>Amice</hi> had been Legitimate, ſhe being of the firſt Venter, would have been more worthy then thoſe of the ſecond, though that be true when the Siſters Claim as Heirs to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet when they come to Claim as Heirs to their Brother (as in this Caſe) if there be Siſters of two Venters, and the Brother be of the ſecond Venter, then the Siſters that are of the ſecond Venter ſhall be preferred before thoſe of the firſt Venter, becauſe thoſe of the ſecond Venter are of the whole Blood. I ſhall therefore here conclude what I have to ſay to your ſecond Reaſon, when I have told you, that I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand why you call this Gift of Earl <hi>Hughs</hi> (as you do in two ſeveral places) <hi>A Releaſe of the Service of one Knight's Fee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your third and laſt Reaſon, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive hath no weight at all; For thoſe Hiſtorians and others which you ſpeak of there, do not take upon them to give an account of all the Children of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok,</hi> but onely to tell who were
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100577:39"/>the Heirs of <hi>Randle Blundevill;</hi> and of this you are ſo ſenſible, That you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs this Argument not to be evincing, and yet it is as ſtrong as your firſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But I cannot but wonder when you name Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> to be one of thoſe that take no notice of <hi>Amicia,</hi> being you well know that he hath mentioned her in his <hi>Britannia,</hi> in his Deſcription of the County of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> and though not as a Coheir to her Brother <hi>Randle,</hi> (for that ſhe was not) yet without the leaſt brand of being a Baſtard: Alſo all thoſe Judges and Heralds, of whom you have formerly heard, and all other perſons (except your ſelf) which have ſeen my Deeds, have from the Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein, been fully convinced, that ſhe muſt needs be Legitimate; and amongſt others, that worthy and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſon, <hi>William Dugdale</hi> Eſquire, our <hi>Norroy,</hi> King of Arms, is of the ſame judgment, as will appear in his <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſcourſe of the Baronage of</hi> England (which will be ſhortly ready for the Preſs.) In which, from the Authorities and Reaſons there briefly cited, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, That <hi>Bertred</hi> was a ſecond Wife, and that <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Lawful Daughter
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100577:40"/>of the ſaid Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> by aformer Wife, though it be not known who that Wife was, and which is worthy obſervation, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> hath heard you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge your Reaſons to the contrary, but did not find them ſuch as to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to him: I hope therefore that I ſhall not becauſe of my Relation to that Noble Lady, be thought to be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial or Singular herein, ſince that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſhe ſtands vindicated by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſo many knowing and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned perſons; but it will neceſſarily follow, that you have dealt very ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with your ſaid Grand-mother, and that upon ſuch weak Grounds, as your <hi>Three Pretended Reaſons,</hi> which will not prove her to be a Baſtard, if thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that were brought on her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, were all laid aſide.</p>
            <p>I have now anſwered the Objections which you have brought againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> the Wife of Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring;</hi> but before I conclude, I ſhall acquaint you, and the Reader, with two Deeds; the firſt whereof, doth belong to <hi>Thomas Ravenſcroft</hi> of <hi>Bretton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Flint,</hi> Eſquire; and the other to <hi>Henry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100577:40"/>Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Kermincham</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> Eſquire, the words whereof do here follow, as they were coppied out ſeveral years ſince from the Originals by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Dugdale</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <p>SCiant praeſentes &amp; futuri quod ego Alanus de Boidele dedi &amp; quiet' clam' fratri meo Willielmo de Boidele &amp; haered' ſuis Doccliſton in feod' &amp; dominicis cum omnibus pertin' infra Limam. Tenend' &amp; habend' de Domino meo Ranl' Com' Ceſtr' &amp; haered' ſuis faciend' ſervicium de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict' terr' ſc. De quatuor feod' &amp; dimid' praenominato domino meo Ranl' Com' Ceſtr. &amp; haered' ſuis. Et ego vero Alanus de Boidele &amp; haered' mei praedict. terr. cum omnibus pertin' praenominato Willielmo de Boidele &amp; haered' ſuis contra omnes homines &amp; feminas cum pertin' warantiſab. Et quia volo quod hec mea donatio &amp; quiet' clam' ſtabilis &amp; inconcuſſa &amp; rat' perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat praeſenti ſcripto ſigillum meum appoſui. His teſt' Domino Ranl' Comite Ceſtr' do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Rad' de Mainwaringhe tunc Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciar' Ceſtr' domino Roberto de Monte alto, Domino Hug' Diſpenſar' Domino Ham' Sen' de Maſcy, Domino Warino de Vernun, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Willielmo de Venables. Toma fil'
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100577:41"/>Willielmi de Goulborn, Petro de Bekering. Rob' tunc perſona Gropenhale ſcriptor' hujus ſcripti &amp; multis aliis.</p>
               <p>SCiant &amp; omnes praeſentes quam futuri quod ego Robertus dominus Moaldie &amp; ſeneſcallus Ceſtrie, conceſſi &amp; praeſenti Karta confirmavi domui ſce' Werburge Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis in Ceſtria &amp; Monachis ibidem Deo ſervientibus totam Villam de Gooſtree plene &amp; integre cum omnibus pertin' ſuis in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram &amp; perpetuam elemoſynam pro ſalute anime niee &amp; animarum praedeceſſorum meorum, liberam quietam &amp; ſolutam ab omni ſeculari ſervicio &amp; omni ſeculari ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actione. Ita quod in eadem Villa de Gooſtre nihil ad opus meum vel haeredum meorum retinui praeter elemoſynam &amp; orationes &amp; tantam libertatem in ipſa eadem Villa prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte domui &amp; praedictis Monachis conceſſi quod in poſterum nullus haeredum meorum quicquid libertatis ſuperaddere poſſit. Et ut hec mea conceſſio rata &amp; inconcuſſa per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneat imperpetuum eam ſigilli mei appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitione roboravi. Hiis teſtibus Rad' de Menilwar' tunc Juſticiar' Ham' de Maſci Gwar de Vern' Rad' fil' Sim' Pho' de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby. Sim' de Thuſchet' Rog' de Menilwar' Willielmo de Venables. Toma Diſpenſatore
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100577:41"/>Rob' fil' Picot' Petro Clerico Com' Ricardo de Vern' Rob' de Menilwar' Brito Paulum Patr' de Moberl' Liulf' de Twamlow. Peers de Surtm' Ran' de Praerſ' Ricardo de Kingsl' Jo' de ſancta Maria, &amp; multis aliis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall alſo deſire you to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what you your ſelf have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in your <hi>Historical Antiquities, pag.</hi> 160. how that Earl <hi>Randle de Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniis</hi> (as doth appear by the Charter there mentioned) did give the Office of <hi>Constable</hi> of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> in Fee to <hi>Euſtace,</hi> Baron of <hi>Halton,</hi> and his Heirs; and did conſtitute the ſaid <hi>Eustace</hi> (to uſe the words of the ſaid Charter) <hi>Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarie Conſtabularium &amp; ſupremum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliarium poſt me &amp; ſuper omnes optimates &amp; Barones totius terrae meae.</hi> As alſo <hi>Pag.</hi> 161. how the Baron <hi>de Montealto</hi> or <hi>Moald,</hi> being <hi>Dapifer, Seneſchal,</hi> or <hi>Steward</hi> of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> in Fee, had the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, which is alſo confirmed by ſeveral Deeds mentioned by you, <hi>Pag.</hi> 129. 130. 139. 144. and 162. In all which, the <hi>Constable</hi> and <hi>Steward</hi> are named before the Juſtice of <hi>Chester,</hi> and all the other Barons; which being
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100577:42"/>ſo, it will be difficult to give a Reaſon (if <hi>Amicia</hi> was but a Baſe Daughter) why Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> in the Deed aboveſaid of <hi>Alan de Boidele,</hi> is named as a Witneſs next to the Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and before Sir <hi>Robert de Monte alto</hi> or <hi>Moald,</hi> Steward of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and ſo many of the other Barons; as alſo in a Deed mentioned in your Book, <hi>Pag.</hi> 139. why the ſaid <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is named next to the Counteſs of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and before <hi>Roger,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> as alſo, why in a Deed in the 143 <hi>Page</hi> of your Book, the ſaid <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> is again named next to the ſaid Counteſs, and before <hi>Ralph,</hi> the Steward of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Legitimate Daughter, the reaſon thereof will be apparent: For though it be true, that the Husband cannot be Ennobled by the Marriage of his Wife, yet the Earl of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> being a Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> and one that is confeſſed by you, <hi>Page</hi> 152 &amp; 159. to have Royal Authority with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, and not unfitly to beſtiled a <hi>Petty King,</hi> having under him his Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> in Fee, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100577:42"/>of the Lord High Conſtable of <hi>England,</hi> and his Steward of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> in <hi>Fee,</hi> after the example of the Lord High Steward of <hi>England,</hi> and his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen about him, in imitation of the Barons of the Kingdom; as alſo his Chamberlaine, who ſupplieth the place of Chancellor, and his Juſtices of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> (who have like power to the Judges of the Courts of <hi>Kings Bench</hi> and <hi>Common Pleas,</hi>) as alſo a Baron of the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> a Sheriff, and other Officers proportionable to thoſe of the Crown: It is no wonder at all, if theſe great perſons did voluntarily give Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence to Sir <hi>Ralph Mainwaring</hi> during his life, in regard he had married a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Daughter to one of their ſaid Earls.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto, that when Earl <hi>Hugh Cyvelioke,</hi> did by his Charter mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by you, <hi>Page</hi> 131. acquit the Abbot and Monks of <hi>Stanlaw,</hi> of ſome Toll in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> (which could be but a little before the ſaid Earl's death, becauſe, the ſaid Earl died in the year 1181. And the Abbey of <hi>Stanlaw,</hi> as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by you, <hi>Page</hi> 267. was Founded but in the year 1178.) The ſaid Earl in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100577:43"/>his ſaid Charter (contrary to all former Precedents which I have ſeen) doth name the Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter</hi> before both the Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and Steward of <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> and the Reaſon thereof, I ſuppoſe to be, becauſe the ſaid <hi>Ralph Mainwaring,</hi> who was Son in Law to the ſaid Earl, was then Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> as he alſo was, ſome years in the life time of <hi>Randle Blundevill;</hi> though the ſaid <hi>Ralph,</hi> as appears, by his aforeſaid Deed made to <hi>Henry de Alditelegh,</hi> did afterwards part with the ſaid Office, <hi>Philip de Orreby</hi> being Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when the ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> was a Witneſs to the ſaid Deed.</p>
            <p>Now this preeminence could not be given to the ſaid <hi>Ralph,</hi> becauſe he was Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter?</hi> (that being below the Offices of Conſtable and Steward, as appears before) but becauſe of the Relation of the ſaid <hi>Ralph,</hi> to the ſaid Earl: But as this reſpect was too great to have been ſhewed him, if he had onely married one that was a Baſtard; ſo it doth not conſiſt with your conceits, that the ſaid <hi>Amice</hi> was Illegitimate, and that the ſaid <hi>Ralph</hi> had nothing elſe with her, but the aforeſaid Services:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100577:43"/>For indeed they were not of ſufficient value to be a Portion ſuitable to the Eſtate of a very mean Gentleman.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>I Have at preſent done with this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, concerning the aforeſaid <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia,</hi> but being deſirous to rectifie all Miſtakes which do concern my Family, in all the Particulars that I can, I think it not inconvenient to inform the Reader of one of yours, in the 334 <hi>Page</hi> of your Book, wherein, ſpeaking of <hi>Margery</hi> the Wife of <hi>Randle Mainwaring,</hi> you ſay,
<q>This Randle Manwaring of Over Peover, ſtiled commonly Honkyn Manwaring in the Language of thoſe times, died <hi>35</hi> H. <hi>6. 1456.</hi> Lib. B. page <hi>21.</hi> E. Buried at Over Peover in the Stone Chappel on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Church: Which Chappel Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery his Wife ſurviveing, erected, with the two Monuments therein for her ſelf and husband, Anno Dom. <hi>1456.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For albeit it be very true, that the ſaid <hi>Randle Mainwaring</hi> did marry <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Hugh Venables,</hi> Baron of <hi>Kinderton,</hi> and Widow of <hi>Richard Bulkeley</hi> of <hi>Chedle</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> yet
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100577:44"/>the ſaid <hi>Margery</hi> did not ſurvive the ſaid <hi>Randle,</hi> and after his death, Erect the ſaid Chappel and Monuments therein: For although on the Eighth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the Year of our Lord God, One thouſand ſix hundred and forty, the Pictures of the ſaid <hi>Randle Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring</hi> and <hi>Margery</hi> were tricked out by a very good hand, as they were then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in a Glaſs Window of the ſaid Chappel, Kneeling, with this Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>Orate pro animabus Ranulphi Mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waryng &amp; Margeriae <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris ejus qui istam Capellam, Anno Dom. <hi>Mcccclvj............</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And although the Year when the ſaid Chappel was built, is ſtill to be ſeen in the ſaid Window, yet that doth not prove, that the ſaid <hi>Margery</hi> ſurvived her Husband <hi>Randle,</hi> and erected the ſaid Chappel and Monuments: For, the word <hi>qui</hi> cannot poſſibly relate to <hi>Margery</hi> alone, but doth, as I conceive, (in the true meaning thereof) relate onely to the ſaid <hi>Randle:</hi> For it appears by an Inquiſition taken after the Death of the ſaid <hi>Margery,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Margery</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:100577:44"/>held in Dower, at the time of her Death (<hi>Ex dotatione Richardi Bulkeley quondam viri ſui</hi>) the third part of the Moity of the Mannor of <hi>Chedle;</hi> as alſo Five Meſſuages in <hi>Middlewich;</hi> One Meſſuage and Sixty Acres of Land and Wood in <hi>Newton</hi> near <hi>Middlewich;</hi> Ten Acres of Land in <hi>Aſhley</hi> and <hi>Hale;</hi> Eight Acres of Land in <hi>Occleston;</hi> Six Meſſuages and Two hundred Acres of Land, Meadow, and Wood, in <hi>Whatcroft;</hi> Six Meſſuages and One hundred and twenty Acres of Land, Meadow, and Wood, in <hi>Holme juxta Davenport;</hi> the Moity of the Scite of one Water-Mill, and Four Acres of Wood in <hi>Little Stanthorne,</hi> and the Moity of the Mannor of <hi>Timperley:</hi> And it is alſo found by the ſaid Inquiſition, that <hi>William de Bulkeley</hi> was the next Heir of the ſaid <hi>Margery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this Inquiſition being taken in the Twenty ſeventh year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth; and the ſaid <hi>Randle Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> together with his Three Sons, Sir <hi>John, William,</hi> and <hi>Randle,</hi> (for the ſaid <hi>John</hi> was Knighted in the life time of his Father) being all Three mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as then living, in a Deed of mine, dated the Saturday next after the Feaſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100577:45"/>of Saint <hi>Hillary,</hi> in the Thirtieth year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth; and I having alſo in my cuſtody another Deed, dated the Sunday next before the Feaſt of <hi>Corpus Chriſti,</hi> in the ſaid Thirtieth year of the ſaid King, made betwixt the ſaid <hi>Randle Mainwaring</hi> the Elder, and Sir <hi>John Mainwaring</hi> Knight, his Son, on the one party, and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Aſhley</hi> of the other party, concerning a Marriage to be had betwixt <hi>Hamnet,</hi> Son and Heir Apparent of the ſaid <hi>John Aſhley,</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> Daughter of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Mainwaring</hi> (which Deed is alſo men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by you <hi>Page</hi> 334.) It is from hence very clear, that the ſaid <hi>Margery</hi> did not ſurvive her ſaid Husband <hi>Randle Mainwaring,</hi> and erect the ſaid Chappel and Monuments therein, after the ſaid <hi>Randles</hi> death.</p>
               <p>There is alſo omitted by you in your <hi>Hiſtorical Antiquities, Agnes</hi> the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>John Mainwaring</hi> of <hi>Over Peover</hi> Eſquire, who was Siſter to Sir <hi>John Mainwaring,</hi> and Wife of Sir <hi>Robert Nedham</hi> Knight: And of this Match, there is very good Proof, (which you have been informed of) I having by me the Pictures of the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert</hi> and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100577:45"/>Dame <hi>Agnes,</hi> as they were carefully tricked out the Tenth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the year of our Lord, One thouſand ſix hundred and forty, from a Glaſs Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in <hi>Holmes</hi> Chappel in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> where they were then Kneeling, with the Coats of Arms of <hi>Nedham</hi> and <hi>Mainwaring</hi> empaled betwixt them, and Three Sons Kneeling behind the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> and Two Daughters Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behind the ſaid Dame <hi>Agnes,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with this Inſcription.</p>
               <q>Orate pro bono Statu Roberti Nedam Militis &amp; Agnetis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xoris ejus &amp; pro animabus Thomae, Johannis, &amp; Roberti filiorum &amp; pro bono ſtatu Matildae &amp; Johannae filia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ejus Roberti fieri in Anno Domini <hi>Mcccccxliiij.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Alſo, in the Chancel of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Adderley,</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> being the uſual Burial place of the <hi>Nedhams</hi> of <hi>Shenton,</hi> in the ſaid County, (which Family of <hi>Nedham,</hi> is now honored with the Title of Viſcount <hi>Kilmorey</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi>) there do yet remain the Monuments of the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert</hi> and Dame <hi>Agnes,</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:100577:46"/>there being on a Blowiſh Marble Stone, the Pictures of the ſaid Sir <hi>Robert Ned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and Dame <hi>Agnes,</hi> and Seven Sons, and Two Daughters; as alſo an Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (all of them of Braſs) which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>HEre lieth Buried under this Stone the Bodes of Syr Robart Nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Knight, and Dame Agnes his Wyffe, Daughter of Iohn Maynwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Pever Eſquyer, which ſayd Robart deceaſſed the</hi> iiii <hi>daye of Iune, An. Domini</hi> 1556. <hi>And the ſaid Agnes deceaſſed the</hi> ii <hi>daye of Maye. Anno Domini</hi> 1560.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:100577:46"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold By <hi>Samuel Lowndes</hi> at his Shop over againſt <hi>Exeter</hi> Houſe in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>DE Jure Uniformitatis Eccleſiaſticae,</hi> or Three Books of the Rights belonging to an Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Churches: In which things, the Laws of Nature, and Nations, and of the Divine Law con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Eccleſiaſtical State with the Civil, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded. By <hi>Richard Davis,</hi> Chaplain to His Grace, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> in Fol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The true Prophecies of</hi> Michael Noſtradamus, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Nineth, Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and one of the beſt Aſtronomers that ever were. A work full of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and learning. Tranſlated by <hi>Theo. de Garencieres,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick, <hi>London. Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aerius Redivivus:</hi> Or the Hiſtory of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, containing the Beginnings, Progreſs, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of that active Sect. Their oppoſitions to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical and Epiſcopal Government, their Innovations in the Church, and their Imbroilments of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Eſtates of Chriſtendom, in the purſuit of their deſigns from the year 1536. to the year 1647. By <hi>Peter Heylyn,</hi> D. D. And Chaplain to <hi>Charles,</hi> the Firſt and Second Monarchs of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Compleat Horſman, and Expert Farrier,</hi> in Two Books. 1. Shewing the manner of breeding good Horſes, with their choice Nature, Riding, and Diet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as well for Running as Hunting; as alſo, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Groom, and Keeper, his true Office. 2. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the moſt exact and approved manner, how to know, and cure, all Diſeaſes in Horſes. A work con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining
<pb facs="tcp:100577:47"/>the Secrets and beſt skill belonging, either to Farrier, or Horſ-Leach, the Cures placed Alphabeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; with hundreds of Medicines never before Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed by any Author. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Famous Conclave, wherein</hi> Clement <hi>the Eight was elected Pope;</hi> with the Intrigues, and Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Devices of that Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Familiar Diſcourſe between</hi> George <hi>a true hearted Engliſh Gentleman, and</hi> Hans <hi>a Dutch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,</hi> concerning the preſent Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Short and Strange Relation of ſome part of the Life of</hi> Taffaletta, <hi>The Great Conqueror and Emperor of</hi> Barbary, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul Feſteau</hi>'s French Grammar, being the neweſt and exacteſt Method now extant, for the attaining to the Purity of the French Tongue. Augmented and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with ſeveral choice and new Dialogues, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Or a View of all Religions in the World, with the ſeveral Church Governments from the Creation, to theſe times; alſo a diſcovery of all known Hereſies in all ages, and places, and choice obſervations and reflections throughout the whole World. Enlarged and Perfected by <hi>Alexander Roſs,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Credulity and Incredulity in things Divino and Spiritual,</hi> (among other things) a true and faithful Account is given of the Platonick Philoſophy, as it hath reference to Chriſtianity: As alſo the buſineſs of Witches, and Witchcraft, fully argued and diſputed by <hi>Merick Cauſabon,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, and one of the Prebends of <hi>Chriſt Church</hi> in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> againſt <hi>Cataline,</hi> In four Invective Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, concerning the whole manner of diſcovering that notorious Conſpiracy, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sermon Preche Devant le Roy a Whitehal. Par le Docteur Tillotſon, Doyen de Canterbury.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Sinners Tears, in Meditations, and Prayers. By <hi>Tho. Fettiplace, Dom. Pet. Cantab.</hi> In Twelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Gentile Sinner, or</hi> England<hi>'s Brave Gentleman Charactered.</hi> In a Letter to a Friend, as he is, and as
<pb facs="tcp:100577:47"/>he ſhould be. By <hi>Clement Ellis, M. A.</hi> Fellow of <hi>Qu. Col. Oxon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Private Devotions, digeſted into Six Letanies.</hi> 1. Confeſſion, 2. Deprecation, 3. Supplication, 4. Thankſgiving, 5. Interceſſion, 6. For the Sick. With Directions and Prayers for the Lords day, Sacrament, Day of Death and Judgment; and two daily Prayers for Morning and Evening. Twenty fours.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
